<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scrutamini scripturas the exhortation of a Spanish conuerted monke: collected out of the Spanishe authours themselues, to reade and peruse the holy scriptures; contrary to the prohibition of the Pope and Church of Rome, whose tyranny in this point plainely appeares to euery mans view. With other occurrences of no small importance.</title>
            <author>Tejeda, Fernando de, fl. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 718:15, 1498:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scrutamini scripturas the exhortation of a Spanish conuerted monke: collected out of the Spanishe authours themselues, to reade and peruse the holy scriptures; contrary to the prohibition of the Pope and Church of Rome, whose tyranny in this point plainely appeares to euery mans view. With other occurrences of no small importance.</title>
                  <author>Tejeda, Fernando de, fl. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [J. Bill for] Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXIV. [1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Fernando Texeda.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 23919.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 23919 on UMI microfilm reel 718.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-b⁴, A-H⁴ (-a1,H4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 718 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy) and at reel 1498 (Cambridge University Library copy).</note>
                  <note>Folger Shakespeare Library copy has print faded, with some loss of text on title page; upper and lower margins cropped, with partial loss of title, page numbers and signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library and the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Reading --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Scrutamini Scripturas:</hi> THE EXHORTATION OF A SPANISH CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERTED MONKE: <hi>Collected Out of the Spaniſh Authours</hi> themſelues, to reade and peruſe the holy Scriptures; Contrary to the Prohibition of the Pope, and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Tyranny in this point plainely appeares to euery mans view.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With other occurrences of no ſmall importance.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Harper</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by THOMAS HARPER. M.DC.XXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6367:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6367:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Right Reuerend Father in God, IOHN, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> Lord Keeper of the Great Seale, and one of His Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Counſell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, My ſingular good Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it runnes in our Spaniſh Tongue: <hi>Quien á buen arbol ſe arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, buena ſombra le cobija;</hi> He that retires himſelfe vnder a good tree, findes both good ſhelter and ſhadow: This I haue found moſt true by my owne experience, in that ſince my voluntary baniſhment out of my natiue Soile, for the peace and libertie of Conſcience, into this flouriſhing Kingdome, like a poore ſtranger, being in a Labyrinth of worldly cares and neceſsities: It pleaſed your gracious Lordſhip, not onely to vouchſafe mee the protection of your Honourable houſe, but (though moſt vnworthy) further to conferre vpon mee many great
<pb facs="tcp:6367:3"/>and important benefits, ioyned with Noble promiſes, of my more preualent preferments, when fit opportunitie ſerued, that I cannot but applie my ſelfe in all the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest offices within my poore power, to manifeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome due and vnfained gratitude. Seeing (as learned <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith) the beſt returne of a benefit, <hi>eſt grata beneficij memoria:</hi> Wherefore, as it hath pleaſed your gracious Lordſhip, to countenance, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the Author, extend the ſame honourable protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and defence, to this his poore labour and worke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the deprauations, and malignities of ſo many powerfull aduerſaries. The Subiect is Diuine, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies ſincere, and the End Religious and profitable; the beames therefore of your honourable and fauourable countenance will ſoone dispell theſe fogges and vapours, Gods true worſhip and ſeruice will hereby bee aduanced, and my vnworthy ſelfe most highly ſatisfied, if vnder the ſhadow and ſafegard, of your honourable wing, I may but liue and die,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt dutifull, thankfull, and faithfull poore affectionate, FERNANDO TEXEDA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_English_nation">
            <pb facs="tcp:6367:3"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE <hi>AND RELIGIOVS Engliſh Nation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His preſent Treatiſe, which here I meane to publiſh and diuulge, I firſt writ and penned in the Spaniſh tongue, with an intention to haue benefitted herein my owne Nation, and ſuch as were in a way, to embrace Gods ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and trueth; which notwithſtanding could take no effect, by reaſon I wanted fit meanes and conueniencie, to print it in the Spaniſh: and then on the other ſide, ſome ſpeciall friends both mooued and perſwaded me, to Tranſlate it into Engliſh, and publiſh it in my owne name, for the better ſatisfaction of this Noble and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Nation, both in regard of what they may feare and doubt of in me, as alſo in regard of what I deſire to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and make knowne &amp; impart to this whole Nation; That as God hath vouchſafed me the ſingular grace and fauour, to diſcerne and embrace the trueth of this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Church and Doctrine; ſo I hope, the ſame mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace, will euer be ready at hand, to fortifie and ſtrengthen me againſt all humane debilities, that if iuſt occaſion be offered, I may moſt conſtantly perſeuere in the ſame to the end, and be prepared (if God ſo ordaine) to ſeale and confirme it with my deareſt blood. And though there haue beene ſome, who after their illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:6367:4"/>and profeſſion of this Tructh, haue with the dogge, returned to their vomite; yet the like ought not to bee cenſur'd and iudged of all: For <hi>Iudas</hi> his being wicked and a reprobate, were no iuſt reaſon to condemne the reſt of the Apoſtles; and ſo though one Engliſh-man ſhould be the occaſion of the vntimely death of another, yet were it no reaſon hereupon, to beare a generall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to the whole Nation: Wherefore, it muſt needs ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue either a weake, or depraued Iudgement, by the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie of one, to preſage and expect the like from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Conſidering, that though there haue beene ſome, who haue reuolted, yet many likewiſe there haue beene, who haue perſeuered conſtantly euen to death. From whom, being good men, we ſhould rather preſume of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtabilitie and perſeuerance, then from the other to conclude ill of all, by reaſon of the errour and leuitie of ſome: Since Chriſtian charitie <hi>(quae non cogitat malum)</hi> obligeth vs to the ſame: and in that it is onely God, who affoords the ſpeciall grace of perſeuerance (euen as hee was the Authour of a good beginning) whoſe power is no leſſe amongſt Italians and Spaniards, then it is ouer other Nations; and who alone is able, and willing, <hi>ex la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidibus, ſuſcitare filios Abrahae:</hi> whereunto let me alſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe this farther, (that I may modeſtly affirme ſomewhat in behalfe of my owne particular nation) very fewe Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards at any time haue beene found, (I ſpeake of thoſe that are learned and vnderſtanding) that euer renounced the Chriſtian faith, which they haue once entertained and embraced, as it may moſt apparently be auerr'd and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by many zealous and learned men, which haue beene and dayly are tormented, and expoſed to the fire by that cruell and tyrannicall Court of the Spaniſh Inquiſition, for maintaining and defending Chriſtian verity and truth,
<pb facs="tcp:6367:4"/>ſo fearefull and terrible a death, together with the iniury herein done both to themſelues and their friends, hauing no power to ſhake their conſtancie, in a Religion which they haue profeſſed and vndertaken. That this is true and infallible, it may be obſerued in more then a fewe Churches of <hi>Spaine,</hi> wherein many <hi>Sanbenitos</hi> are han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vp (which are not like thoſe <hi>Sacci benedicti</hi> in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, impoſed vpon true and deuout penitents, but rather <hi>Sacci maledicti</hi>) which are certaine written Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, wherein are regiſtred the death, and puniſhment of ſuch good Chriſtians, whom they haue expoſed to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull and ſhamefull death for this Religion, which they terme <hi>Caluinian,</hi> or <hi>Lutherane.</hi> And were it not for this bloody and cruell proceeding of the Inquiſition, the Pontificall Religion would at this day be ſoone baniſht out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and in ſtead thereof, by Gods aſſiſtance and furtherance, true Religion planted and eſtabliſhed; as Doctor <hi>Ylleſcas</hi> plainely auerres: while he much laments and grieues, for the ſmall number of Chriſtians at this day. In <hi>Spaine</hi> (ſaith he) what ſhould we now haue been, if thirteene yeeres ſince, the diabolicall conſpiracies of <hi>Cazalla</hi> and <hi>Conſtantino</hi> had not beene diſcouered.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ylleſcas</hi> enlae prefacion y ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumento ſobre el vlt. lib. de la hiſtoria Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical, y Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</note> Theſe infernall conſpiracies, whereof this Authour ſpeakes, were (to the great heart-griefe, both of himſelfe and all other Papiſts) the pure and ſincere profeſſion of true Chriſtian Religion. This <hi>Cazalla</hi> (of whom this Author ſo infamouſly reports, euery one ſpeaking as hee is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) was a Doctor of Diuinitie, of ſingular vertue and vnderſtanding, who in the yeere 1557. was burnt in <hi>Vallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid,</hi> for the Proteſtant Religion, together with his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, brothers, and ſiſters, and a Knight of ſpeciall good quality, called <hi>Don Carlos,</hi> as alſo the Marques of <hi>Poza</hi> ſonne, and many others, were exceedingly afflicted and
<pb facs="tcp:6367:5"/>perſecuted: the houſe, whither they vſed daily to repaire to heare the word of God, was raſed downe, and ſowed with ſalt, that it might neuer be reedified: and in the middeſt of this houſe,<note place="margin">This Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne I haue ſeeene with mine owne eyes.</note> they ſet a marble pillar, for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall, that there faithfull Chriſtians (whom they call <hi>Hereges Lutheranos</hi>) were woont to aſſemble. <hi>Constantino</hi> alſo was a Doctor of as profound and great learning, as <hi>Spaine</hi> in many ages had brought forth. Hee was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and Confeſſor to that renowmed Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, and by this meanes, if he had affected it, he might haue riſen to very eminent dignities; but all this he reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and contemned, (as a man that made no account of theſe worldly honours) and went to <hi>Seuilla,</hi> where he was taken by the Inquiſition, and dying there, his body was afterwards burned by order of the ſame Inquiſition. His followers (whom this Author ſpecifies) were very rare men, both for their learning and liues, who oppoſed themſelues, and in Pulpits publikely preacht againſt the tyranny, doctrine, and proceedings of the Pope, and the Inquiſitors; explaining ſincerely to the people, the trueth of Chriſts ſacred Goſpel, to ſuch wonderfull benefit and emolument of all the faithfull, that in the ſame time, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue eight hundred were taken and impriſoned for this cauſe, by the Inquiſition, onely within the compaſſe of the Citie of <hi>Seuilla.</hi> Some of them were rich people, and of very good quality, both men and women; among which number, was <hi>Don Iuan Ponce de Leon,</hi> brother to the <hi>Counte de Baylen,</hi> and couſin to the Duke of <hi>Arcos,</hi> a Gentleman queſtionleſſe of ſingular pietie and integritie; and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Ioana,</hi> wife to the Lord of <hi>Higuera,</hi> whom, preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her child-bearing, the Inquiſitors expos'd to a torment called <hi>del Burro,</hi> in the caſtle of <hi>Triana,</hi> and the torment was ſo great, that ſhe died thereof: for the cords pierced
<pb facs="tcp:6367:5"/>euen to the marrow bones of her armes, her thighes and legges; and in this her affliction and torment, they caried her backe againe to priſon, in a maner dead, ſhe vomiting blood out of her mouth in great abundance, her very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes being rent and torne: in the end, ſome eight dayes after theſe torments, ſhe died, hauing no body neere, or about her, no not ſo much as a damoſell, who a few dayes before, was cruelly handled and tormented as her ſelfe was. Many of this number thus impriſoned and taken, were afterwards burned, which they did, by twentie and twenty at a time; the reſt were moſt barbarouſly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanely entreated; the houſe where they congregated was defac't, and vſed after the ſame maner as that of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zalla</hi> was in <hi>Valladolid.</hi> Let the courteous Reader peruſe that religious and learned mans worke, <hi>Cyprian de Valera,</hi> in his peculiar Treatiſe of the Authoritie of the Pope, where he relates theſe perſecutions more at large: And to a booke entituled, <hi>Inquiſitto Hiſpanica,</hi> written firſt by a Spaniard in Latine, &amp; afterwards tranſlated into Engliſh, where both theſe, and many other ſorts of torments are deſcribed, wherwith they perſecute the faithfull in <hi>Spaine.</hi> But that which hath been deliuered, ſhall ſuffiſe me at this time: whereby it may appeare, that if it were not for the ſtrictneſſe of that rigorous Inquiſition, there would excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many and faithfull good Proteſtants, daily manifeſt and reueale themſelues; and yet notwithſtanding the ſame, and all their cruelties vſed, there are in many parts ſome: all which may iuſtly excite a charitable and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conſtruction of thoſe, that leaue thoſe Kingdomes, and repaire into other Dominions, that they may there, with all Chriſtian liberty, truely worſhip and call vpon Gods holy Name. And let none be ready to reproach vs (as many vſe to doe) with a Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> or ſome
<pb facs="tcp:6367:6"/>other famous Impoſtor, and ſubtill Spie; for God forbid we ſhould all be made of the ſame metrall: for as the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh prouerbe ſaies, <hi>Todos los dedos de la mano, no ſon yguales;</hi> There's difference betwixt one man and another. Beſides, the many and ſingular commodities we haue beene ready to leaue and forſake in our owne Countreys, and the innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable troubles, pouerties, diſcontentments, and diſtaſts that we meet withall in forreine parts, yeeld no weake nor ſlender teſtimony, that God doth graciouſly intend to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the good worke he hath already begun in vs. And in my opinion, a man hath no reaſon to forbeare the doing of good to another, in that he is fearefull and miſtruſtfull of his doing ill; becauſe in this caſe we ought not ſo much to reſpect the perſon whom we benefit, as him, for whoſe cauſe we are moou'd to any commiſeration or pity; and this is God. Neither in like maner, is it a good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable courſe, for the attracting and bringing of a man to any good, and to abett and vphold his perſeuerance therein, to draw backe our hands from his reliefe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour; for this were enough in them vnſtable, and not inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and habituated, in afflictions and calamities, to make them murmure with the Iſraelites in the wilderneſſe, and to cry out againe after the fleſhpots of Egypt: Although for my part, I am confident by Gods affiſtance and grace, notwithſtanding all worldly contrarieties, that I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conſent or yeeld to ſo odious a Renunciation, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I thanke God, well inſtructed and prepared and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and hope ſo to continue in this maine point and maſter-peece of Chriſtianitie, that, <hi>per multas tribulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; calamitates, oportet nos ingredi regnum Dei.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6367:6"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll the beatitude &amp; felicity of man, conſiſteth in the not failing to chuſe aright that, which moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth him, and to diſcerne what it is he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſheth, and what it is hee imbraceth; and this the Philoſophers call prudence, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to be <hi>recta ratio rerum agendarum,</hi> and teacheth a man to order all his actions by the rules of reaſon: There is a worldly wiſedome, and a celeſtiall wiſedome; the first hath the earth for its ſcope and obiect; the ſecond aymes at heauen. Some mens liues are full of errours and blurres, both in corporall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall matters; other mens comportments are diſcreete and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable: the difference floweth from the qualitie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whereof ſome are prudent, others are imprudent: the one ſort faſteneth on that which is good, the others grope euen as blinde men at mid-day. If a man erre in temporall things, the dammage is not great; for all ſublunary occurrences are of ſmall conſequence, and to miſcary in a ſlight affaire, imports little. For his errour is repairable, in that there is another life; but if a man erre in matter of eternity, which is for euer permanent, and incapable of any amendment or alteration; this is the greateſt detriment a man can incurre. For the declining whereof, God hath giuen the ſacred Scripture, the onely meanes to know, vnderstand, and diſtinguiſh which is the true, and which the falſe Religion, what kinde of worſhip, and manner of ſeruice and honour hee enioyneth and approoues of, and what hee inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and deteſteth: but Sathan, the father of lies, and author of darkenes, perceiuing that by this way alone, his fraud is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled, his darkeneſſe diſsipated, and the vanity on which his
<pb facs="tcp:6367:7"/>kingdome is grounded luculently detected, whence reſults his eminent ruine. Finding by the long experience of his loſſes, that ſuch miſerable men as he hath captiuated vnto death, and bound with the chaines of ignorance and blindneſſe, being irradiated with this heauenly light, doe eſcape out of his priſon, and are tranſported into the liberty of the ſonnes of God. Hence it comes to paſſe that though by the quality of his peruerſe and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diſpoſition, he abominates and perſecuteth all the means that ten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the good and ſaluation of mankinde, yet with more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular diligence, and extraordinary violence, he hath euer oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; will neuer intermit to reſiſt (vntil God altogether bridle him vp) the bookes of ſacred Writ. Now amongst all the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and wars which he hath ſtirred vp againſt it, that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by the interuention of his truſty Agents, the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> and the Inquiſitors of <hi>Spaine,</hi> doth at this day proſecute againſt it, is, without all compariſon, moſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent and cruell. For (to omit thoſe other infamous aſperſions they cast vpon it) there being allowed, in thoſe countreys, where the Inquiſition reigneth, an infinite number of bookes repleate with a thouſand blaſphemies, ſuperstitions, deluſions, lyes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſties, and turpitudes, to the great preiudice and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of numberleſſe ſoules, they prohibite the reading of holy Scripture vnto the common people, quite exiling it from them, and moſt ſhamefully calumning it to bee the cauſe and occaſion of errours, and the inſtigatrix to vice. It is true, that <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth gaue order to the Biſhops and Inquiſitors, that with the conſent of the Parſon, or Confeſsor, they ſhould licence the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scripture in the vulgar tongue, to ſuch as could reade it with fruit: Hereby intimating, and that not obſcurely, that his meaning was not, that they ſhould reade it, who were incited thereunto by a deſire of knowing and inquiring into the trueth, but onely ſuch as by auricular confeſsion, their courſe of life, and behauiour, had giuen ſufficient teſtimony, that they were most obſtinate Papists, and ſuch as had ſworne vnto the Popes words.
<pb facs="tcp:6367:7"/>But let the beneuolent Reader obſerue, that all that was granted by <hi>Pius,</hi> were it much or little, yet ſo much as hee permitted, hath been all abrogated and annihilated by a Bull of the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentle <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth of infamous memory, as may bee ſeene in <hi>Caſtigatione indicis librorum prohibitorum;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably whereunto are interdicted all the holy Scriptures in the vulgar tongue, in the Catalogue of prohibited bookes made by the Cardinall <hi>Quirogua,</hi> in his ſixt rule; as alſo in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent one compiled by the order of Cardinal <hi>Bernardo de Rojas</hi> and <hi>Sandoual,</hi> in the fourth Rule: and yet not thus content, the ſaid ministers of Sathan, ſend into all parts their familiars (which are other incarnate deuils, of inferiour authoritie to them, but of no leſſe cruelty and ſagacitie) who night and day goe from houſe to houſe, and from company to company, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues to bee friends and familiars withall, being in trueth enemies and familiar deuils. And by this meanes they knowe and diſcouer, if there bee any, that flying the contagion of diſſolute bookes, betake themſelues to the Sanctuary of the holy Scriptures, labouring to reade them in the vulgar tongue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they vnderſtand not the other languages in which they are compoſed, if they take a Lay-man that's skill'd onely in the Spaniſh with this Diuine booke in his hands, it were better for him, they had ſurprized him coyning falſe money, or machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome notable treaſon againſt his Prince or naturall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, for that his offence and rebellion ſhould be leſſe cruelly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, then the reading of holy Writte in the mother tongue is wont to bee.</p>
            <p>This great truculency and vnheard Tyranny of the Pope and Inquiſitors, the deplorable blindneſſe, and the lamentable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude of thoſe that are ſubiect vnto them, eſpecially of thoſe of my Nation, haue cauſed me to take vp my penne, to doe that in my owne language, which many graue and religious Doctors haue happily accompliſhed in other tongues, to the wonderous and plentifull benefit of the faithfull; to wit, to euince and
<pb facs="tcp:6367:8"/>point out as with the finger, the preciſe neceſsitie and obligation that all ſorts and conditions, both of men and women haue to reade and meditate on the holy Scriptures, whether they be rich or poore, learned or vnlearned, ſmall or great ones; and that not onely if the Prelats permit it, but alſo though they ſhould all inhibite it. The reaſons and arguments which I will alleadge for this purpoſe, are either drawne word for word, or collected by neceſſary conſequence out of Spaniſh bookes (two or three La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine bookes excepted) all which are imprinted in <hi>Spaine</hi> with priuiledge, and (as you may ſee in the Frontiſpice of all of them) haue been examined and approoued, not by one, but by man Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and not by the leſſe but by the moſt learned men, and not by thoſe that were the leaſt, but the greateſt Papists; ſo that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Catholique Romane, eſpecially if he bee a Spaniard, may reade and peruſe this my booke without any ſcruple of conſcience, and cannot chuſe but giue credit to what he readeth in it. My intendement herein hath been to gratifie my Nation, as alſo that forreine nations, which profeſſe the true Religion and faith, and particularly the Noble Engliſh Nation, in which it flouriſheth more then in all the reſt, and to which I ſtand more obliged then to all others, may ſee, that the ſtrength of the truth we maintaine, is ſo forcible, that maugre all the power of Hell, Pope and Inquiſitors, it is manifeſted &amp; diuulged by the mouth of it's enemies. And this will be more perſpicuous in thoſe other Tractates, which if God vouchſafe me his Diuine grace, and my neceſsitie and pouertie affoord me time, place, and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I will bring to light. In which I will prooue, by authorities I haue already gathered out of Spaniſh Authors and Bookes, the principall points of our Engliſh Religion againſt the Romane. God grant it may all be to the honour of his holy Name, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his Church, which ſhall be the maine remuneration and guerdon I moſt deſired of the labour I beſtowed in this Worke, and the reſidue I purpoſe to imprint hereafter; which how great it hath been, <hi>iudicium ſit penès doctos.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6367:8"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That all the faithfull, whatſoeuer be their <hi>profeſsion and condition, are preciſely</hi> obliged to Reade and Meditate the Diuine Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Trueth firſt appeareth in that God would haue it ſo, and commands it, as the enſuing authorities out of Scripture it ſelfe auerre, the which are allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Spaniſh Authors cited in the Margin. <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph) <hi>are they who diligently meditate vpon diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> To know God by the teſtimony of them; <hi>Reade, and ſearch</hi> (ſaith Chriſt our Lord) <hi>the Scriptures, for they teſtifie of mee:</hi> Hereunto alludes that of Deuteronomie,<note place="margin">Aluarado to<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> primero del arte de bien viuir, fol. <hi>1091.</hi>
                  </note> Chap. 22. <hi>Aske thy father, and hee will declare vnto thee; thy Anceſtors, and they will tell thee.</hi> For as Father <hi>Serpi</hi> cloquently teacheth, The writings and Scriptures whence wee ſhould knowe and learne, are no other then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Euangeliſts, and Apoſtles, whoſe Bookes wee all enioy. And to theſe, ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serpi en el tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tade <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio, pag. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> (as Father <hi>Serpi</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this ſaying) wee muſt approach to gather learning and profit from them. But that of <hi>Moyſes</hi> tranſcendeth all theſe teſtimonies (as Father <hi>Luys de Granada</hi> noteth) as the moſt Illuſtrious and pregnant one,<note place="margin">Granada en el preambulo de la <hi>2.</hi> P. de la intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ion del Symbelo.</note> to conuince all vnderſtandings, who hauing propounded and declared the Law of God, ſaith on this wiſe; <hi>Theſe words which I now ſet before thee, ſhall bee in thy heart, and thou ſhalt teach them to thy children; and ſhult thinke of them when thou art
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6367:9"/>in thy houſe, and when thou iournyest; when thou goeſt to bed and when thou riſeſt vp againe, thou ſhalt faſten them as a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to thy hand, and they ſhall bee, and mooue before thine eyes, and thou ſhalt write them in the galleries and portals of thy houſe.</hi> With what other words (wee may ſay with <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada</hi>) could the conſideration and ſtudie of the Law haue been better exemplified; and as if all this had been little, in the 11. Chapter of the ſame Booke, hee againe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it to vs in the ſelfe ſame words, (a thing which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome happens in the Scripture) ſo great was the care of this heauenly man (who ſpake with God face to face) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired wee ſhould haue to be aſſiduous in the Law of God, as who well vnderſtood how much wee were bound ſo to doe, and the ineſtimable fruits and benefits that would follow of it. The ſame God that without making diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Sexe, age, or qualitie, enioyned all to reade the ſacred Scripture, did likewiſe ordaine that it ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged in all languages, that all might haue the fruition of it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leon</hi> en el prologo de los nombres de Chriſto.</note> So doth the learned Father, <hi>Luys de Leon,</hi> confeſſe it in theſe words, That God compiled the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with very plaine words, and in a language which was vulgar and familiar to them, to whom hee firſt gaue them. And when fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, together with the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Ieſus Chriſt, this treaſure was transferred and communicated to the Gentiles, hee cauſed them to bee explicated into diuers tongues, and almoſt into all thoſe which at that time were moſt generall and common, that they might bee obuious and familiar vnto all. And to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the trueth hereof, wee reade that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it into his mother tongue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prades</hi> en el prologo de la adoration delas imagines.</note> which was the Dalmatique: And <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> into the Armenique tongue. <hi>Vlphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> a Gotiſh Biſhop into the Gotiſh tongue, as Doctor <hi>Prades</hi> relateth of all the three. <hi>Iohn,</hi> Prelate of <hi>Seuill,</hi> tranſlated it into the Arabique, as Father <hi>Mariana</hi> ſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6367:9"/>who ſaith, that the ſaid Prelate did it with intendment to promote the increaſe of all Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mariana</hi> en la hiſtoria de Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panua lib. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi> tomo primero.</note> and helpe the Mores, for that the Arabique tongue was of ordinary vſe among all. And hee addeth that there are ſome copies of this tranſlation which haue been propagated to our times, being yet extant in ſome places of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Mariana</hi> ſaith, that the King, <hi>D. Alonſo</hi> the tenth,<note place="margin">Idem ibidem lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the holy Books of the Bible to be tranſlated into Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Would to God the moſt mighty <hi>Philip</hi> the fourth would command the like worke now. Holy Scripture hath been imprinted many other times in the Spaniſh tongue, and ſometime in the Valentian tongue, as the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may ſee in the exhortation which the moſt learned and religious <hi>Cypriano de Valera</hi> made, inducing to reade it; which accompanieth the verſion which hee with great labour and ſtudie made, and cauſed to bee imprinted, which is the laſt time (that I knowe) it hath been printed in our tongue. I would it might pleaſe God that it were turned into all languages, as alſo into our Spaniſh, he, in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings, can mooue the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Kings, to permit vnto our Countrey men the Spaniards, the fruition of this inualuable treaſure, for the foreſaid pious Gentleman, for the good of our Nation imployed twenty whole yeeres labour in the ſaid tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which in the iudgement of all the learned is a very excellent one.</p>
               <p>Alſo the trueth of the former propoſition appeareth (to wit, that all the faithfull are obliged to reade and ruminate the holy Scripture,) in that the holy Doctors and ancient Fathers exhortes all thereunto.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> en la guia eſpiritual fol. <hi>291. Prades</hi> en el prologo de la hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoria de la ad<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racion de las imagines.</note> Father <hi>Puente</hi> doth clearely teach this, as you may ſee in the place quoted in the Margent. So likewiſe Father <hi>Prades</hi> doeth openly confeſſe it, though hee adde that notwithſtanding this, the Catholike Church, to wit, the Romane, did prudently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6367:10"/>and holily in prohibiting the vulgar to reade the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that you may ſee how the Papiſts eſteemed the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the holy Doctors, when they ſpeake (which they oft doe) againſt their errours and tyrannies.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambulo de la <hi>2.</hi> part. de la introduecion del Symbolo.</note> 
                  <hi>Luys de Granada</hi> approoues our propoſition; and in proofe of it alleageth that which S. <hi>Hierom</hi> wrote to a Virgin, by name <hi>Demetria,</hi> recommending to her the reading of ſacred Scripture:<note place="margin">Hiero. <hi>ad</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</note> and giues the ſame aduice to S. <hi>Paula,</hi> and yeelds this reaſon of it, that the true nouriſhment of the ſoule, is to meditate day and night on the Law of the Lord, and S. <hi>Bernard</hi> writing to his ſiſter, perſwades her to this ſtudy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reremde modo bene viuendi, c. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> declaring vnto her particularly the fruits and effects of this good reading. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> counſelleth his diſciple <hi>Timothie,</hi> who was full of the holy Ghoſt, that till hee came, hee ſhould bee exerciſed in reading the holy Scripture, which <hi>Timothie</hi> had learned from a childe. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Torres</hi> is of the ſame minde with <hi>Granada,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Torres</hi> lib. <hi>25.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi> de la Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophia de Principes.</note> and brings to ratifie his opinion almoſt the ſelfe ſame examples and teſtimonies which the other did; and addes that S. <hi>Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> recommends the foreſaid ſtudy of Diuine Scripture, vnto <hi>Theodoret</hi> the Senator.<note place="margin">Fulgent. epiſt. <hi>6.</hi> ad E.</note> Of S. <hi>Hierome</hi> Father <hi>Guſman</hi> recordeth, that he wrote to a Father, and in another place to a mother,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Guzman</hi> en ſu libro de los bie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes del Inneſto trabajo, fol, <hi>24,</hi>
                  </note> that they ſhould enure their daughters to reade and vnderſtand the holy Scripture. <hi>Gregorie Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzene</hi> (ſaith Father <hi>Reynoſa</hi>) aduiſed out of his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,<note place="margin">Ad laetan de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione filiae.</note> that the Bible ſhould neuer part out of the heart, nor out of the mouth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reynoſa</hi> fol. <hi>87.</hi> del maeſtro Chriſtiano.</note> nor out of the vnderſtanding, nor out of the tongue, by reaſon of the admirable benefits which redounded from the aſſiduous vſe of it.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> amongſt all the reſt of the Fathers, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry admirable in this point, and particularly in his third Sermon that hee made of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> where he anſwereth to all the obiections that the Papiſts at this day make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the free and vulgar vſe of the Bible. The Reader
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6367:10"/>may pleaſe to peruſe the Exhortation, which moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly <hi>Cypriano de Valera</hi> made, to perſwade men to reade continually the holy Scriptures, where hee ſhall find the maine and principall ſumme collected, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> deliuers in that place.</p>
               <p>Beſides that formerly deliuered, we doe prooue, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe neceſſitie and obligation, wherein all the faithfull ſtand bound, to reade the holy Scriptures, becauſe in the Primitiue Church and many ages after, all ſorts of people did ſo, and it was counted a great offence, not to reade them: and that this reading was very behoouefull and profitable for them, the moſt learned Doctor <hi>Leon</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes moſt clearely, ſaying;<note place="margin">Leon en el Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo de los nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres de Chriſto.</note> In the firſt ages of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, and many yeeres after, it was eſteemed a great fault in the faithfull, not to be often conuerſant in the peruſing and reading of the Diuine Bookes: and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall men, and thoſe whom we call Secular, both learned, and vnlearned, for this reaſon, treated ſo much of this exerciſe and ſtudy, that the carefulneſſe herein of the vulgar ſort, ſtirred vp in Biſhops and Prelates, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtudy and practiſe in the ſame; who ordinarily in their Churches, in a manner euery day, expounded the ſacred Scriptures to the people, becauſe the particular reading of them by euery one in their houſes, by the light of that publike doctrine, being illuminated, and gouerned as it were by their Maſters and Teachers voice, might be free from errour, and be a cauſe of the greater and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant benefit; which in very deed was ſo great, as that order and gouernment was religious and zealous, and the fruit was anſwerable to their ſowing of the ſeede. And Maſter <hi>Prades</hi> confeſſeth as much in this point, as <hi>Leon,</hi> in theſe words; In ancient times the holy Scriptures were propounded to the people in the vulgar tongue, that ſo all ſorts of people might reade them; the which was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6367:11"/>profitable, and as ſuch approoued of many holy and very learned men.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Reading of the holy Scriptures, prooued very profitable,<note place="margin">Prades en el Prologo de la adoracion de las imagines.</note> many Spaniſh writers affirme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: but amongſt all thereſt, Father <hi>Torres</hi> auerres the ſame admirably, with wonderfull examples of many who were cur'd and reform'd by the ſame. The which I will heere expreſſe and ſet downe with all poſſible breuitie,<note place="margin">Torres lib. <hi>25.</hi> de la Philoſophia de Principes. Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> that the propounded veritie may more euidently appeare. The firſt example produced by <hi>Torres,</hi> is of the Eunuch, ſeruant to <hi>Candaces</hi> Queene of Ethiopia, who by the meanes of reading the Prophet <hi>Eſaias,</hi> attain'd to the knowledge of Chriſtian veritie. The ſecond is, of <hi>S. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia,</hi> who deſiring to be aſſur'd of the infallible know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of her ſaluation, the Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paul</hi> came to her hands, (this would not haue happened to her if ſhee had beene in Spaine) vpon the doctrine whereof ſhe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and meditating, ſhe in ſuch ſort grew to diſcouer the falſities and deceits of the Gentiles, and the veritie of Chriſtian wiſedome, that ſhe was not onely conuerted to the faith and beliefe of our Lord, but further, ſhee was martyred in defence, and for the confeſſion of the ſame. The third example that he propoundeth is, of that illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious <hi>Domina,</hi> who was a Martyr of Ieſus Chriſt; who being a Gentile, no leſſe prudent then honourable, and being brought vp in the Palace of the Emperour <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian,</hi> by chance ſhe met with a booke of the ſame Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and with the Hiſtory written by S. <hi>Luke,</hi> of the Acts of the Apoſtles; in whoſe doctrine, ſhe diſcouered the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Infidelitie; and ſo becomming a Chriſtian, ſhee embraced a cruell death, to keepe poſſeſſion of that ſhee had vndertaken. To the former examples he addes this other, of that moſt illuminated S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who being plunged in a thouſand doubts and ambiguities, it was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6367:11"/>ſaid vnto him, <hi>Tolle &amp; lege:</hi> Take and reade: and hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying this voice, not knowing from whom, or whence it came, hee tooke the Epiſtles of the Apoſtle, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, the firſt which preſented themſelues to him, were thoſe wordes written to the Romanes, Chap. 13. <hi>Not in eating and drunkenneſſe, but put yee on our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe reaſons ſo farre preuailed with him, that preſently abjuring his hereſie, hee was conuerted to the Lord. The laſt example propounded by this Author, is incomparably beyond all the reſt, and ſufficient to mooue vs, neuer to be without the holy Scriptures in our hands; which is, the ſame of the moſt holy Virgine, the Mother of him that is Lord of heauen and earth, who at the ſame time, when ſhe felt in her ſacred entrailes, the moſt diuine myſterie of the Incarnation, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Angel, S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayes, that ſhee was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and meditating on the Propheſie of <hi>Eſaias,</hi> Chap. 7.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Luc. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ecce Virgo concipiet, &amp; pariet filium, &amp;c.</hi> whereunto <hi>Torres</hi> addes, That wee may conceiue, how the reading of the holy Scriptures, was a ſingular preparation for the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſuch a fauour and grace; the which he confirmes, and this renowmed S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerues in the bleſſed Virgine; amongſt whoſe many excellencies, hee ſpecifies one, namely, that ſhe was very well read and conuerſant in the Prophets. Many other examples the ſame Father <hi>Torres</hi> mentions, which heere I omit to auoid prolixitie; and becauſe theſe aboue declared, euidently demonſtrate, that the vſe and reading of the holy Scriptures, hath euer beene common and commendable in all the faithfull; and that the peruſing of them, hath brought foorth wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects; which is the ſame we aimed at in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and which for more efficacie, we now briefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme by the example of S. <hi>Gertrudis,</hi> with whom (if wee may beleeue the Papiſts blaſphemous fiction) our Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6367:12"/>did marrie; and moreouer that our Sauiour Chriſt ſayd Maſſe on the day of his nuptials, that they might be the more ſolemne and authenticall: For this bleſſed Nunne, is wonderfully exalted by Maſter <hi>Granada,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada en el li. de la inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de la dinina Pedad, fol.</hi> 22. Note that this Booke is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the graueſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in all <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </note> in that ſhe was very perſeuerant in reading of the holy Scriptures, and in that ſhee confirmed whatſoeuer ſhe ſpake, out of the Texts, both in the one and th'other Teſtament; who, if ſhe were now in Spaine, I make no doubt but ſhe would be reputed a Lutherane. Wee alſo prooued more in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, in what an obligation all the faithfull ſtand bound to reade the diuine Scriptures, becauſe it is Gods pleaſure we ſhould know and vnderſtand him by them. <hi>Lorenzo Iuſtiniano</hi> teacheth as much, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Fray Ioſeph. de Ieſus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> followes,<note place="margin">Fray Ioſeph. cap. <hi>12.</hi> del libro de las excelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias de la ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtidad.</note> and alledgeth in theſe words: By meanes of the holy Scriptures, our Lord meant to illuminate and inſtruct our ignorance, informe and direct our faith, and fortifie and ſtrengthen our hopes. The very ſame, Father <hi>Arinçan</hi> openly confeſſeth and maintaineth, ſaying, that the holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Arinzano en ſu Roſario, fol. <hi>138</hi>
                  </note> is a Booke plaine and delucide, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger, which God imparted to vs, that by the ſame wee might know him. But aboue all theſe Teſtimonies, that of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> conferring with God in prayer, and ſpeaking of himſelfe, propounds vnto vs, and Father <hi>Lewys</hi> of Granada auerres and confirmes the ſame: Whereas I was weake and inſufficient (ſayth S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi>) to finde out trueth, with naked reaſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtood in need of the teſtimonie and authoritie of the holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Granada en la ſegnuda parte de la introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion del Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo.</note> I began then preſently to conceiue, how it was not poſſible to beleeue, that thou (O God) wouldeſt giue ſo great a diuinity, and power to theſe writings in the world, but that by their meanes thou wouldeſt be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and by them ſought out. Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thus farre, the which the Biſhop of <hi>Tortoſa</hi> alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, to prooue, what we haue formerly propounded:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6367:12"/>and he addes, That God gaue vs the Scriptures eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by them to finde out Chriſt, whom (as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith) the Scripture ſounded in his care. From this, it muſt needs infallibly follow, that whoſoeuer takes away the vſe of the holy Scripture from the vulgar, together with them, they take away the onely meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which God gaue them, to know himſelfe, and his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt; and ſo conſequently they ſhut againſt them the gate of eternal life, which wholly conſiſts in this knowledge, and the ſame Ieſus Chriſt teſtifieth, ſpeaking to his heauenly Father, from which alſo we may collect, how deepely we ſtand bound and obliged to the reading of the ſame holy Scripture, if wee meane to know God, and obtaine euerlaſting life.</p>
               <p>The ſaid obligation and bond, is alſo made more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, wherein all Chriſtians ſtand bound to reade the holy Scriptures; for as God will be beleeued out of them, ſo he will likewiſe by them be ſerued and reuerenced: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in them hee reueales vnto vs his Diuine will and pleaſure, and hee ſent amongſt vs his holy Law, which the vulgar can no wayes obſerue nor keepe, if they be not permitted to looke into it. They will peraduenture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, how this reaſon onely prooues, that euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to know, and vnderſtand the Law of God; but hereof it doth not neceſſarily follow, that the reading of the holy Scriptures is requiſite for all in generall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſufficient, that the Doctors and great Maſters propound to the vulgar, whatſoeuer is moſt neceſſary and requiſite therein to be knowen. Firſt, I anſwere this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, That Gods will is not, the people ſhould onely heare and vnderſtand, what their Teachers and Paſtors thinke good, but that all and euery good Chriſtian and faithfull man, ſhould ſearch and looke into the Scriptures, as formerly hath beene ſufficiently prooued: As alſo it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6367:13"/>is further auerred, becauſe as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> teacheth, and next to him the Biſhop of <hi>Tortoſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rena, in Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>og. in totam Scripturam, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> all Scripture is diuinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and written by the holy Ghoſt to this end, that as a common medicine of the ſoule, all men in generall, and euery man to himſelfe in particular, might apply a fit and proper remedy. Conformable to this, S. <hi>Baſil</hi> teacheth, whom Doctor <hi>Fonſeca</hi> cites and followes; For as the eyes which behold all things, and cannot ſee themſelues, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in ſome glaſſe that repreſents them to our ſight; ſo likewiſe our ſoule, viewing and beholding all things, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee nor diſcerne her ſelfe, but onely by looking into the glaſſe of the holy Scriptures. Hereupon it followes, that the reading thereof is requiſite and expedient for all men, in that it is befitting, that all men ſhould both ſee, and know themſelues: But the Pope of Rome will not permit the vulgar people to ſee and behold themſelues in this diuine glaſſe, that they may not diſcerne how odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abominable the falſe doctrine he profeſſeth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Chriſtian ſoule in the ſight of God: imitating herein the Ape or Monkie, who breakes the glaſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it layes open his owne vglineſſe and deformity: and herein alſo reſembling that ancient <hi>Lays,</hi> who caſt away her glaſſe; whereof <hi>Auſonius</hi> made this Epigram:
<q>
                     <l>At mihi, nullus, in hoc vſus, quia cernere talem,</l>
                     <l>Qualis ſum, nolo, qualis eram, nequeo.</l>
                  </q> All which (as by his daily workes it appeares) the Pope alledgeth of the diuine glaſſe of the holy Scriptures, for the vſe he makes of them is but ſmall, or none at all. Moſt true it is, that there is this difference betweene the Pope and <hi>Lays;</hi> for ſhe hated her owne deformitie, and not the glaſſe; but hee loues his owne deformitie, and abhorres the holy Scripture: for he reueales and manifeſts it to all the world. But let this ſuffiſe for this time; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let vs anſwere the reaſon propounded to vs, for in that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6367:13"/>we are commanded, to prooue and try the ſpirits, becauſe Sathan many times transformes himſelfe into an Angel of light: from hence it comes to paſſe, that the reading of the ſacred Scriptures is neceſſary for all men; which teach vs, how wee ſhould diſcouer masked and hollow enemies, and thoſe inwardly deceitfull; ſhewing vs alſo what we ſhould retaine, and what to auoid, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> affirmes, and next to him Father <hi>Ieſus de Maria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fr. Ioſeph. en el cap. <hi>12.</hi> del lib. de la ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtidad.</note> And queſtionleſſe, if it be not lawfull for vs to looke into the Scriptures, wee ſhall ſo hardly be able to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene bad and good, the faire and deformed, what God commands, and ſo what himſelfe prohibits, as a blinde man can iudge of colours, becauſe it is only the Scripture that repreſents vnto vs all theſe things without any error or deceit. If it be not ſo as I ſay, let a Papiſt tell me that neuer ſaw the Bible, how can hee trie the ſpirits whether they be of God, or of the deuill? how can he diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Gods and the Popes commandements? By the word of God he cannot, becauſe he neuer read it, nor heard it read, but only in a tongue he vnderſtood not; which is as much as if he heard it not at all. It may be he will reply, that he knowes ſufficiently, becauſe the Pope and his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats haue ſo taught him. But thus I anſwere, He is ſubiect to a thouſand errors and deluſions; for how can he but be deceiued, who ſuffers himſelfe to be led by the noſe, by thoſe men who are deepely intereſſed in the ſame things they command,<note place="margin">Gueuara ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gund parte, del monte Calua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, fol. <hi>702.</hi>
                  </note> ſeeing (as <hi>Antonio de Gueuarra</hi> notes) no man obſerues loyalty and fidelitie, where peculiar intereſts doe diſtract him; and the ſame <hi>Gueuarra</hi> ſaid, The Lord is onely he, that opens our ſight that we may clearely ſee, and who points out vnto vs the way wherein we muſt walke, and remooues the ſtones that they annoy or offend vs not, and aduiſeth vs what wee are to doe in all things. Now therefore, ſuch a Papiſt as neuer lookt into the Bible, muſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6367:14"/>needs be ignorant and indiſcreet, and therefore he cannot auoid the running into innumerable errours; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſafeſt courſe is, to repaire to the holy Scriptures, which, without any deceit or ambiguity, will informe him in whatſoeuer hee ought to beleeue, or ſtands obliged to be; for they are the moſt approoued and authenticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, leanning to no falſitie, and therefore they are called Canons or Rules, becauſe conformable to the ſame, <hi>Vt per Lydium lapidem, fidei dogmata ſunt examinanda,</hi> as the Biſhop of <hi>Tortoſa</hi> prooues out of S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> authoritie;<note place="margin">Tena. ibid. fol. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> and as the ſame Biſhop ſaid, The Scripture is called the olde and new Teſtament, <hi>quia ſicut in Teſtamento, mens &amp; voluntas Teſtatoris continetur, ita in ſacra Scriptura, mens Dei qui illius verus eſt Teſtator.</hi> As alſo it is like a Letter or Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle which God writes to all the faithfull, wherein hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueales vnto them his will, and what he requires from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one,<note place="margin">Puente, Tom. <hi>3.</hi> tratado <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as both S. <hi>Gregory</hi> &amp; Father <hi>Puente</hi> teach. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I conclude, that all the faithfull in generall, none excepted, ſtand preciſely obliged and bound, to reade and meditate in the holy Scriptures: Becauſe it is requiſite for all men to examine whether their faith be true or falſe, all men muſt needs vnderſtand the will of their heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, expreſt in this letter and Teſtament; and as he ſhould be accounted an vngratefull and inhumane ſonne, that did contemne to reade and peruſe the deed and Teſtament of his Father, to know thereby his Will, and to put it in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; ſo with farre greater reaſon, he ought ſo to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, that regards not the Diuine Scriptures, becauſe they are the letters and writings, wherein our eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King of kings and Lord of lords, hath declared his will and pleaſure, and what he requires from vs. If any one,<note place="margin">Puente en la Guia ſpiritual. fol. <hi>298.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> &amp; next to him Father <hi>Puente,</hi> ſhould receiue letters from an earthly Emperour, he would not ceaſe till hee had read them, and vnderſtood what they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6367:14"/>comprehended, to fulfill it: how therefore can thy ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe be ſo great, that the heauenly Emperour, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſent thee his Letters and Certificates for thy good, thou ſhouldeſt neglect and not reade them. Study there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I pray thee, euery day, and reade and meditate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually on the words of thy Creator, conceiue and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Gods meaning in his owne wordes, for in them his diuine meaning and will is expreſt, there you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his ſublimity and condition, the loue he beares thee, and what he would haue thee to doe, to giue him content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: What <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Puente</hi> ſpeakes to all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, I tell it now to you, noble and diſcreet Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, (and let it be lawfull for me to ſpeake freely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly) I beſeech you, affectionately to tell me, what would you thinke of a man, vpon whoſe life it ſtands to knowe the will of his father, to put it in execution; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing meanes to vnderſtand the ſame without ambiguity or doubt, by his laſt Will and Deede, he yet deſires to bee informed of another, that goes about to delude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, would you not hold ſuch a man for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt foole and ſot liuing? Certainely if you doe thus, you cannot but perceiue, that you commit the ſame and a greater folly: and therefore when you know that your heauenly Father hath left you his diuine Will, manifeſted and reuealed in his Teſtament, and the Letters Patents of of the holy Scripture, and that on the knowledge or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it, your euerlaſting glory or damnation depends, you neuertheleſſe making ſmal account of this diuine Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and letter, repaire to the Romane Biſhop, to bee informed of your heauenly Fathers Will, being true, that the Pope is but a man, as others are, (if peraduenture hee bee not a woman, as Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was) giuen to deceiue and to bee deceiued, whom it ſo neerely concernes that you ſhould not know the will of God; for your knowing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6367:15"/>of it euidently and perſpicuouſly, would but cauſe his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and perdition. In a word, deare Countrey-men; open your eyes at laſt; and ſeeing you are ſo ſubtill and adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the fluxible and momentany things of this life, giue not occaſion to all the world to ſay, that you are fooles and indiſcreete in matters that ſhall for euer be permanent in the future life; and whereas without ſparing any labour, you goe inuironed with a thouſand perils vnto the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt parts of the world, induced by I know not what pride and ambition, which euer ſwayeth in you, (and are dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and miſpriſed by other Nations) to ſubiugate thoſe who neuer were in ſubiection, and to impoſe your yoake on the neckes of ſuch as neuer vnder-went it; bee not ſo ſenceleſſe and ſo cowardly, that for feare of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> you omit the peruſing and ſcrutiny of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Letter which the Emperour of heauen hath dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to leaue you, by the reading whereof you ſhall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite your ſelues from that deplorable ſeruitude, into which the Romiſh Antichriſt hath plunged you, &amp; ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt your ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infinite tribute which you pay to him and his Miniſter: and which is more, by Gods aſſiſtance, you ſhall attaine the knowledge of the true Religion and Chriſtian faith, and bee able to iudge betweene good and euill, that which is ſeemely, and that which is vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, betweene vertue and vice, and finally betwixt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, and the Popes Iniunction, which you ſhall neuer bee able to doe, if you reade not holy Scripture, and which therefore are exceeding behooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to you, and to all that deſire to ſerue God as they ought.</p>
               <p>Beſides that before alleadged,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> en la guia ſpiritual. fol. <hi>401</hi>
                  </note> we may prooue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe neceſſitie of reading the holy Scripture by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in that God meant by them, to enlighten our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, (which is a cauſe of all evills, as thoſe Authors no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6367:15"/>in the Margent, moſt learnedly prooue and teſtifie,<note place="margin">Marquez, en ſu Teſoro en la Epiſtola dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoria.</note> and indeede the thing of it ſelfe is ſo cleare and manifeſt, that it needes no proofe nor teſtimony.) Father <hi>Ieſus de Maria,</hi> confirmes this trueth in the ſame wordes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. Father <hi>Albarado</hi> is of the ſame opinion;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambulo, de la ſegurda parte, de la Introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion y en el pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo del memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe bookes (ſaith hee, which we are euioyn'd to to reade) the holy Scripture hath the firſt place, which was dictated by the holy Ghoſt, to illuminate our vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and to make them holy. Father <hi>Serpi</hi> confeſſeth as much, ſaying, The diuine Scriptures,<note place="margin">Fr. <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> en el lib. de la caflid. ad. cap. <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> diſſipate the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and cloude of ignorance, and therefore the reading of them is expedient for all men, in that it concerneth all men not to be ignorant.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Albarado</hi> tom. primero del arto de bien viuir, fol. <hi>390.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing you, beloued Countreymen (that in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it may be lawful for me to exhort you) are inuolued in the palpable and Aegyptian darkeneſſe of ignorance, as dayly experience teacheth vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serpi</hi> de purga. torio, cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> which all godly and learned men (whom God raiſeth vp amongſt you) do lament; be no more rebellious and oppoſite to this diuine light of the holy Scripture, for whoſoeuer are ſo, they will haue ill ſucceſſe, and one of your great Doctors learnedly notes.<note place="margin">Granada <hi>ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
                  </note> He that goes out of his houſe in the night, hee caries with him a Torch, or a Lanthorne, and he that doeth not ſo,<note place="margin">Marquez ibid. fol. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> is in danger to fall or ſtumble; and in the night and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this life, the Scripture muſt be the light,<note place="margin">Vaſcones en el deſterro de igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia en la E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtola dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria.</note> to guide and conduct vs, except we meane to trippe and ſtumble at euery ſteppe, as the ſame Author ſets downe: wherefore, moſt deare brethren, you ſhall doe exceeding well, if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſell and aduiſe of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> you be intentiue and obſeruant of the diuine Word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Prophets, as one that is conducted by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendant and bright Torch in an obſcure and darke place, while the light of the true day breake foorth,<note place="margin">Fonſeca <hi>2.</hi> p. del amor de Dios cap <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and that the Authour of light, may riſe and ſhine in your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6367:16"/>hearts: but ſo you doe wonderfull ill, if according to the Iniunctions and Mandates of the Pope, you do not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and giue eare to the ſame.</p>
               <p>And if you would know why that ſame ſucceſſor to S. <hi>Peter</hi> (as hee boaſteth himſelfe to bee) teacheth doctrine quite contrary to that of S. <hi>Peter</hi> in this particular point, I will plainely and briefly expreſſe it to you; The word of God explained in the holy Scriptures, is, (as before wee ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> and <hi>Dauid</hi> affirmes the ſame) a lanthorne that giues light to our ſteppes, wherein we may plainely conceiue the propertie it hath to diſtinguiſh good men from bad. Fowlers when they follow their game by night, vſe to carrie burning lights, with which they dazell the fowle, who perceiuing the light, fall into the Fowlers nets; ſo they catch Partridges: and of Doues the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſayes, comparing the captiuitie of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> to the Doue or Turrle, taken by this deluſion and ſtratageme. Birds properly ſeeke after the light, though thereby they loſe their liberty; but on the contrary, wilde and ſauage beaſtes are enemies to the light; for the Lion, or Wolfe, and ſo all other beaſts, perceiuing the ſame, they ſhun it, as they would doe a conſuming fire, and being aſtoniſhed, they flie to their Caues, and Dennes. In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Internall light of the ſacred Scriptures, diſcouers which are the birds that raiſe their flight towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and who the wild and ſauage bee that runne and hide themſelues in the Caues of the earth: <hi>Peter</hi> (that wee may come to the point) is a bird that bends his flight vp towards heauen, and ſo hee imbraceth the light of the Scriptures, and hee would haue vs guided thereby; but the Pope is a wilde and ſauage beaſt, (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifies in his <hi>Apocalypſe</hi>) and therefore hee abhorres and ſhunnes this diuine light, and loues darkeneſſe, in which like to other beaſts, hee commits his rapine and robberies, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6367:16"/>becauſe this may not come to your notice, he prohibites you the holy Scripture: But if you affect the ſaluation of your owne ſoules, and would not bee enſnar'd with the deluſions and ſubtilties of the deuill, but haue the darke fogges and miſtes of ignorance taken from before your eyes, though the Pope and hell it ſelfe combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe prohibite, yet you ought to lay hold of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine light, and not to goe one ſteppe, in the darke night of this life, without the ſame.</p>
               <p>Alſo the neceſſitie and obligation that all the faithfull haue to reade and meditate on the ſacred writings, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted from afflictions which cannot bee wanting in this life; <hi>Seeing</hi> (as holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>all this life is but a long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 7.</note> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>that our aduerſary as a raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Lion goes about euery where ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> And the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> magnifieth the ſtrength and great power of this enemie, and furniſheth vs with diuers kinds of ſpirituall weapons to foyle him with.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambulo de lae <hi>2.</hi> parte de la introduccion del Symbole.</note> This argument which I haue abridged, Father <hi>Luys de Granada</hi> vſeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that the books of ſound &amp; good doctrine are altogether requiſite to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people. Amongſt which reaſons, if this be of validitie, who wil be ſo blaſphemous, as to denie it, to be good in the ſacred &amp; Canonical books. For what doctrine in the world can be paraleld with that which God himſelfe inſpired his ſeruants the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles withall, to enlighten our vnderſtanding, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie them, as we ſaid elſwhere, &amp; of which the ſame God ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Eſaias; I am the Lord thy God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. cap. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee profitable things,</hi> that is, <hi>things which in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent degree deſerue the title of profitable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> en la guia eſpiritual. fol. <hi>292.</hi>
                  </note> as Father <hi>Puente</hi> elegantly obſerueth. So that this argument might ſuffice without farther explication, to authorize our purpoſe: Howbeit, we will not ſo leaue it, but will compendiouſly ſhew, that in the ſacred Scriptures moſt effectuall reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6367:17"/>are found for all dangers that can aſſault vs in this life, and that without it a Chriſtian cannot extricate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out of them; and thence it appeares, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, is preciſely neceſſary vnto all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First holy Scripture is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> ibid. fol. <hi>292.</hi>
                  </note> as Father <hi>Puente</hi> faith, with <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, a ſhoppe of all wholeſome things, to care euery ſicke perſon that commeth to it:</hi> and <hi>Puente</hi> addeth, <hi>that in it we ſhall find ſufficient remedie for all euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fonſeca 2</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te del tratado del amor de Dios, cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>wherewith to heale the ſoule: It is</hi> (as <hi>Fonſeca</hi> obſerueth) <hi>not onely a gener all antidote against the griefes of the ſoule, but alſo a lenitiue and eaſe for the euils that befall the body:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambuio. de la <hi>2.</hi> parte de la introduccion.</note> 
                  <hi>And alſo</hi> (as Father <hi>Luys de Granada</hi> auerreth) <hi>it is th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t celeſtiall Manna which had the reliſhes of all meates, becauſe there is no taſte or effect which a ſoule can deſire to haue, which it may not ſind in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, it is</hi> (as the ſame <hi>Granada</hi> noteth) <hi>that royall table furn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d with all meates, of which the Prophet ſpeaketh, Thou O Lord haſt prepared a table before me, which giues me ſtrength and ſubſiſtence against all my enemies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fonſeca <hi>ibid. fol.</hi> 64.</note> 
                  <hi>It is</hi> (as <hi>Fonſeca</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly alleadged, teacheth) <hi>an armoury againſt all the force of the deuill, and against the ſnares of hell; and a tower, as that of</hi> Dauid <hi>full of all manner of weapons, against all kinde of temptations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> ibid fr. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> en ſu libro de caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad. fol. <hi>160.</hi>
                  </note> as Father <hi>Puente</hi> affirmeth. <hi>It is armour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, and weapons to offend our enemies,</hi> ſaith Father <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Ieſus Maria.</hi> And he addes, that therefore S. <hi>Bernard</hi> writes to one of his ſiſters, <hi>that ſhee ſhould fence her ſelfe with diuine Scripture, and that ſhee ſhould endeauour to rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in her prayer, that which ſhee ſhould rea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e therein, becauſe it would ſerue her not onely for a defence in this life, but alſo for a particular helpe to obtaine the life to come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſtella <hi>1.</hi> parte del libro de la v<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>idad del mundo. fol. <hi>96.</hi>
                  </note> And Father <hi>Stella</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>That nothing beſides God in this life is more ſweetely receiued, nor reliſheth more deliciouſly, nothing ſo much ſegregateth our ſoule from the loue of the world, and nothing ſo comforteth and fortifieth the ſouldier of Chriſt againſt all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as the frequent reading of the holy Scripture.</hi> If then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6367:17"/>the excellencie and valew of the weapons of the ſacred Scripture, be ſo great, as well in defending vs againſt our aduerſaries, as in offending them, who can bee ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as to denie, that the reaſon which aboue wee allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the Father <hi>Granada</hi> in fauour of bookes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing good doctrine, is not much more forcible, and that without compariſon in Scripture.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore we formerly mentioned that whereof the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> putteth vs in minde, that <hi>our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as a rauenous Lion enuironeth vs on all ſides to deuoure vs:</hi> and the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſetteth before vs the might of this aduerſary, and prouideth vs with diuers ſorts of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to vanquiſh him, and play the conquerours. It will be fitting that wee conſider what theſe weapons are, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be onely the deuoute bookes, and not the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, or profane books not tending to deuotion, which as wee ſhall hereafter ſee, are at this preſent flouriſhing in the Papacie, or the ſacred and Canonicall; of which my Argument treateth. This, one <hi>Brauo</hi> a Spaniard will ſhew vs, whoſe authoritie may not be vnderualued, ſeeing in matter of Armes, that of the <hi>Brauo</hi> was euer in repute. This Spaniard <hi>Brauo</hi> tells vs, That the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brauo en la vigilia magna, fol. <hi>89.</hi>
                  </note> who obſerued the maner of arguing with the deuill vſed againſt vs, gaue vs the forme of anſwering him; <hi>Cuireſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stite fortes in fide: Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſiſt ye, being ſtedfaſt in the faith and doctrine of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> And a little after, the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Sumentes ſcutum fidei in quo poſsitis ownia tela nequiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi ignea extinguere:</hi> For he oppoſeth to this fire the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp;c. But what doctrine is this? perhaps its that which occurres in the bookes of <hi>Amadis</hi> and <hi>Belh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſe;</hi> or in the bookes which the Pontificall Doctors bring to light; or in the Canonicall ones of holy Scripture. Let vs here attend to this Doctor, for hee will tell it vs. <hi>Not</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>the doctrine which is inſperſed in pernicious books,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6367:18"/>in amorous letters, in ſugred complements, which ſome out of curioſitie through their depraued inclination make their ſtudy,</hi> (for this is to adde fire to the deuill, and to ſtrengthen his enemy) <hi>but ſacred, ſpirituall, and holy doctrine, which is of greater force.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> Whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>Ignitum eloquium tuum vehementer: Thy word is very fiery,</hi> and if wee haue recourſe to the trueth of his Goſpel, to his counſell, to the Commandements of Gods Law, and be firme and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable in them; This diuine fire is ſuch, that it will conſume all the artificiall and deluding fire of the deuill. Hitherto are <hi>Brauos</hi> words. See yee not, that the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſend vs, not to aſſume weapons againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of our enemy, from bookes of meere deuotion, much leſſe from profane ones, but from the Canonicall of holy Scripture? And why ſhould they not direct vs vnto it?<note place="margin">Granada en el preambulo de la ſegunda parte de la introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion del Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo.</note> for as the ſame <hi>Granada</hi> ſayth, <hi>What are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the Chriſtian warrefare, what the ſpirituall ſword that cutteth off vices, but the word of God?</hi> And as hee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, <hi>With what other weapons did our Captaine fight in the deſert with the enemie, but by infirming euery temptation by ſome word of Scripture?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Trinit. c. <hi>13.</hi> Puente tem. <hi>2.</hi> de la perfecion, fol. <hi>255.</hi>
                  </note> Teaching vs with his example, to draw from it the trueths and remedies wherewith we are to ouercome all our temptations, as doeth note with Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> Father <hi>Puente.</hi> And from it only did the Church in the time of the Martyrs, draw matter of conſtancie; in the time of the Doctors, knowledge; in the time of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, the confutation of their errors; in time of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, humility and temperance; in time of ſupineneſſe, matter of feruencie,<note place="margin">Reynoſa en el maeſtro chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ano, fol. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> as the Father <hi>Reynoſa</hi> noteth: of what elſe but that, ſaid famous S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> whom the ſaid <hi>Reynoſa</hi> citeth and followeth; that, <hi>quicquid homo extra didicerit, ſi noxium eſt ibi damnatur, ſi vtiles eſt ibi inuenitur: Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man learneth out of it, if it be hurtfull its there condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if it be profitable, its found there:</hi> and wee neede not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6367:18"/>goe ſeeke it elſewhere. And that we may not defatigate our ſelues, of what but the holy Scripture ſpake S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>it is profitable to inſtruct the ignorant, to refute error, to reprooue ſinne, to teach righteouſneſſe, to perfect a Chriſtian, and make him complete in euery good worke?</hi> which is as much as if he ſhould haue ſaid, that it comprehendeth all things neceſſary to our ſaluation; as forthwith the moſt learned Father <hi>Puente</hi> will demonſtrate eloquently and copiouſly.</p>
               <p>We will conclude from what hath beene ſaid, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtles themſelues, that informe vs of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes and temptations of our enemies, doe ſend vs to holy Scripture, thence to take weapons wherewith to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie vs, and withſtand them, becauſe it is the armour of the Chriſtian warrefare; that to it all the faithfull ſhould repaire, becauſe all are obnoxious to temptations, and that if the Pope diſpoile the common people of theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine weapons, it is that he may warre againſt them, and ſell them at his pleaſure: whereof I will elſewhere diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>In confirmation of the precedent Argument, I thought good to prooue more at large, the ſufficiencie of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture in all things neceſſary to our ſaluation, that it may appeare the better, that its worthy to be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently conuerſed in by all, ſeeing it compriſeth all that is neceſſary to all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6367:19"/>
               <head>The holy Scripture containeth all things <hi>whatſoeuer is neceſſary for</hi> Saluation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor <hi>Aluarado</hi> clearely teacheth this truth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aluarado</hi> tomo primero delarie de bien Viuir fol. <hi>454.</hi>
                  </note> who, when hee affirmed that God had conſtituted in the Church the neceſſary and fit meanes to obtaine the ſame, and theſe meanes are reduced to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſpeciall heads, hee ſets them downe in order, ſaying: The firſt is true faith and the knowledge of the true God: and our Mediatour and Redeemer Ieſus Chriſt. The ſecond meanes is his holy Law, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all the commandements of things requiſite and neceſſary, to enter into eternall life, and all the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which may aſſiſt vs, to attaine vnto it, with ſecurity and perfection. The third is Religion, and the ſincere worſhip of God, with ſuch externall rites and ceremonies as are belonging to God. The fourth meane, are the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. The fift, are ſeuen rare and excellent vertues, faith, hope, charity, prudence, iuſtice fortitude and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, together with ſeuen ſpeciall gifts and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the holy Ghoſt. The fixt, is internall doctrine, and the light of inſpiration, and illuſtration from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: and for the exterior, it muſt proceed from lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Maſters and Doctors, who, both by example and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, teach whatſoeuer is expedient to bee knowen or vnderſtood, for to rayſe ſoules vp to heauen. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth meane, is the diuine and ſacred Scriptures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6367:19"/>are reuealed all things by vs formerly mentioned. Whatſoeuer hath beene deliuered comes from this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, who, though he were a blacke Monke by Order, and profeſſion, yet heerein he hit the white of Chriſtian verity and truth, and of the ſufficiencie and validity of the holy Scriptures: As alſo Father <hi>Torres, Teetino</hi> (which is a leſuite) deliuered this trueth: I <hi>te atino</hi> (which in Spaniſh ſignifies as much as I embrace this trueth) when he ſaid: that S. <hi>Paul</hi> referred <hi>Timothie</hi> to the Scriptures, wherein he might learne whatſoeuer was fit and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for him, the which if the Pope would preach and teach to his diſciples and followers, all thoſe traditions which hee ſels vnto vs for neceſſary faith, and are not to be found in the Scripture, would be ſuperfluous, and of no moment at all. For if in the Scriptures wee meete with all things neceſſary, there is nothing out of them that can be eſteemed neceſſary. As a philoſophicall Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om plainely prooues which ſayes: <hi>qui totum dicit, nihil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brauo</hi> en la Vigilia magna. fol. <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> Doctor <hi>Brauo</hi> manifeſtly acknowledgeth the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer truth propounded in theſe words: The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a glaſſe wherein a man may clearly &amp; perſpicuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerne whatſoeuer is requiſite in an humane life, for the true ſeruice and worſhip of God. But, beyond all theſe Authors, Father <hi>Puente</hi> is admirable vpon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect (&amp; as in other arguments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> toro <hi>3.</hi> de la ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecion. fol. <hi>711.</hi>
                  </note> ſo in this more eſpecially againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) for not in one, but in many places, he auers and prooues this veritie with words very ſignificant, and moſt preualent reaſons. I meane not here to ſet downe all that I haue read and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued throughout his bookes, about this particular point, in that I would not willingly be prolix, as alſo becauſe I conceiue, that what I ſhall hereunder mention, will be more then ſufficient. And in the New Teſtament (he firſt ſaith) that all the Law Euangelicall was fully
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6367:20"/>declared. Whereupon it muſt needes of neceſſitie enſue, that in the New Teſtament is comprehended whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is neceſſary for ſaluation. For of this, there is no doubt to be made but that the Law of the Goſpel is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in it ſelfe to ſaluation. This Author in another place ſaies,<note place="margin">Idem en la guia eſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. fol. <hi>291.</hi>
                  </note> The ſacred Scripture, is the cleareſt glaſſe where we may beſt ſee and behold thoſe countenances which we haue ſet downe: that is to ſay, the glorious countenance of God, that of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; then our owne. Becauſe in the ſame are reuealed, all thoſe vertues which appertaine to the perfect knowledge of theſe three things. Moreouer it preſcribes vs remedies againſt vices, armes againſt temptations, aduice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in doubts, conſolation in ſorrow, eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation, from labours and troubles, and due Meanes, whereby to attaine to the perfection of all vertues. For as S. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſaith, that is, the table which diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome placed in the Church plentifully furniſhed with Bread and Wine. For on the ſame is ſet the bread of life, and of vnderſtanding, which are the ſolid and firme truthes, from whence the vertues take their life and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the knowledge of things eternall, as alſo, there is the wine of ardent and zealous affections, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the water of wholſome knowledge, to giue ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, vigor, and ioy vnto the heart. It is the Pantry of the King of Heauen, and the Cellar of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious wines, whereinto hee brings his elect, and there he quencheth the hunger and thirſt they haue of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. It is an open ſhoppe, full of medicines, for all maner of ſpirituall infirmities: and a tower, like that of <hi>Dauid,</hi> repleniſhed with all manner of armes, againſt euery kinde of temptation. For in that it is a table full of delicates,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> it is placed as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes, to defend vs, againſt thoſe that vex and perſecute vs. For which cauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6367:20"/>S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, that all Scripture inſpired from God,<note place="margin">2. Tim. cap. 3.</note> is profitable to inſtruct, to conuince, correct, and inable to euery good worke; that euery man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and well inſtructed in euery good worke: as if hee had ſaid: It is very effectually to teach vs neceſſary trueth for our ſaluation, and to conuince ſuch enemies, who with falſe and colourable reaſons pretend and ſeeke to deceiue vs, and to correct our vices, and exorbitances, and to fortifie vs in the exerciſe of vertue and good works; that ſo we may attaine to that perfection, whereunto wee are called, and to the end thereof, which is eternall life, which is ſaid to bee found in the holy Scriptures, which manifeſt him, who is our eternall life, and the meanes left vnto vs, to purchaſe him. All this aboue mentioned, is ſet downe by Father <hi>Puente,</hi> the which, though in it ſelfe it be much, yet is it but little in reſpect of that hee writes in another place, explaining the ſame place of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, his reaſons tranſlated word for word, euen as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent citations were, are theſe which follow.</p>
               <p>Another excellencie of the ſacred Scripture is,<note place="margin">Idem <hi>4.</hi> toma fol. <hi>560.</hi>
                  </note> that the ſame is very beneficiall to ſaluation, and that perfection, which wee pretend. Becauſe the holy writings (ſaid the Apoſtle) <hi>Poſſunt te inſtruere ad ſalutem;</hi> They can informe thee in whatſoeuer is requiſite for thy ſaluation. And a little after, they are not onely profitable for euery one in particular, but further they are good and behoofefull for others: and in this reaſon S. <hi>Paul</hi> recounts fiue great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities for one of the fiue ends. The firſt is, <hi>ad docendum,</hi> for the teaching of men all that is requiſite for ſaluation, &amp; perfection, that ſo through ignorance they may not bee depriued of them; and it doeth not onely explaine the trueths therein mentioned, but alſo other verities, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to naturall Sciences: for that corrects and directs many things, and if it were not for the light wee receiue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6367:21"/>there-from, wee ſhould repute many things for true that are but counterfait and falfe. The ſecond end is, <hi>ad argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum,</hi> that is, to confute and conuince, thoſe that follow and vphold hereſies, and contrary errors: For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſets downe ſuch ſtrong reaſons, and arguments, as are ſufficient to ſubdue them, and to refell their vaine arguments. Euen as wee may plainely ſee by the reaſons, wherewith Chriſt our Lord, reprehended and conuinced the Iewes, and in thoſe, produced by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, againſt many Heretikes, and Schiſmatikes. The third end is, <hi>ad corrigendum;</hi> that is, to correct vice, and rebuke the guilty, becauſe the ſame preſcribes rules of correction, and points out thoſe things that are to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, together with a meanes to reforme them. The fourth end is: <hi>ad erudiendum in Iuſtitia,</hi> to inſtruct them in righteouſneſſe and equitie, becauſe it doth not only teach ſuch verities, as enlighten the vnderſtanding, but alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the doctrine of vertue, which mooues and excites the minde to loue and imbrace them, propounding all thoſe motiues, meanes, and benefits, which ſtirre vp a man to put them in practiſe: and finally ratifying after an excellent manner that formerly vttered, ſaying; <hi>Vt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ſit homo Dei, velomne opus bonum inſtructus:</hi> For it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines not ſatisfied, in the ſimple teaching of any vertue, but in deciphering an high and compleate perfection in them all: that the man of God may be perfect, and well inſtructed in all manner of good workes, and in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of all vertues, from the meaneſt to thoſe which are moſt excellent, and ſupereminent. A little vnderneath: The fulneſſe of all wiſedome is found in the two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the New, and Old. Thus farre proceedes the ſame Authour: and thus, with that formerly alleadged, I haue ſufficiently expreſſed the propounded trueth, of the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and all-ſufficiency of the holy Scriptures: from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6367:21"/>whence wee alſo gather (to returne to our purpoſe) how preciſely and ſtrictly Chriſtians are bound to reade, and be often conuerſant in the holy Scripture: For, what can be more neceſſary for them, then that which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends and containes all that is behoofefull and requiſite, to liue here a life of grace, and afterwards to obtaine a life eternall, which in the ſame is expreſſed and manifeſted.</p>
               <p>And now it is time we ſhould come to the obiections of our Aduerſaries, againſt the vſe and free reading of the Bible in the vulgar tongue. Their firſt reaſon is; that as Chriſt himſelfe taught, <hi>Holy things muſt not bee giuen to dogges, nor pearles to ſwine,</hi> whereby they conclude, with a ſtrange and deprau'd ſubtilty, <hi>that the precious Margarite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>or Pearle of the Scripture, ſhould not be commited to the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the vulgar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt of all I anſwere thus to this reaſon, that the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and bond in this caſe is very great, wherein Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtand bound to the Pope and his Miniſters, ſeeing they honour them with ſuch a glorious, and Illuſtrious title, as that of ſwine, and dogges. Secondly I anſwere, that whereas there are diuers that tearme themſelues Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, to whom many Eccleſiaſticall perſons are not to be compared, for ſanctitie and puritie of life; yea, who many times are worſe then the moſt reprobate Seculars, (as in another place we will prooue) therefore the Pope and the Inquiſitors (if they would onely communicate the Scriptures to men holy and deuout) they ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take it from bad Eccleſiaſticall men, and permit them to the good Secular ſort; but ſeeing they doe not ſo, but freely grant them to all Eccleſiaſticall perſons, both good and bad, and contrariwiſe detaine them from all both good and bad indifferently, if they be Seculars, it is a ſigne, that they do not prohibite the Bible to the vulgar, becauſe they are as ſwine, but becauſe they ſhould be ſo, euen as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6367:22"/>indeed they are, for the moſt part vnder the Papacie. Thirdly I anſwere, that to bee holy it is not ſufficient to vnderſtand <hi>Latine,</hi> neither can the ignorance of it be any cauſe of not being holy, and therefore, if the Pope thinke that it is not iuſt nor reaſonable, to permit the Scriptures to any other but ſuch as are holy, he herein manifeſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be moſt vniuſt, allowing it onely to all thoſe, that vnderſtand the <hi>Latine,</hi> (as he thinks) and prohibiting all ſuch as vnderſtand it not; as if to vnderſtand <hi>Latine,</hi> and to be holy were <hi>einſdem ambitus &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uertibile.</hi> To the fourth I anſwere; in the ſame words, with which Doctor <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> ſatisfies them that oppoſe the ſaid place of S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> againſt the common and vulgar vſe of the Bookes of Mother <hi>Tereſa:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gratian</hi> en ſus obras, fol. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Theſe bookes (ſaith <hi>Gratian</hi>) are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to come into the hands of ſwine, which are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and ſenſuall men, who trample and tread vpon God: For they wil neither ſpend money in buying of them, nor time in reading of them, neither weare out their wittes to vnderſtand them, being content with their own wiſedom, in the pleaſures and delights of the world; becauſe, for our ſinnes, ſuch men delight rather in bookes of Cheual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and vanities, then in Bookes of ſpirit and deuotion. And if any man read, and then contemne or calumniate the ſame, (as if they were an Inſtrument to ſalue and worke ſome good effect in a Chriſtian ſoule) hee would be content to ſuffer as well as he that made them, calling to minde, that the Lord, for the ſaluation of ſoules, would himſelfe be contemned, ill intreated, peſecuted, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, of the moſt baſe, abiect, and abominable people of the world: And if any for want of vnderſtanding, or in malice of heart ſhould erre, or ſhew ſcandall in this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall doctrine, let him lay the blame on his owne malice, or ignorance, and not on the Bookes which giue a light to thoſe that haue good eyes: but they that will reade
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6367:22"/>them with eyes dazled through philartie and ſelfe-loue, ſuch are not blinded with the doctrine of Spirituall Bookes, which are no more in fault for their blindneſſe, then the Sunne is in fault, that the Batte is blind, euen as the fault is not to be imputed to the Sunne, that the Bat is blinde, but to the defect of its eyes; ſithence the Eagle beholds it directly, without any detriment of ſight. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heretiques patronize their hereſies by a miſinter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſacred Writ, and yet neuertheleſſe we may not ſay that Scripture hurteth, and ought not to be read. All theſe are the words of Doctor <hi>Gratian,</hi> to whom the Pope and the Inquiſitors owe many gratulations, ſeeing here with admirable grace hee ſtops their mouth, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward they may not open it, to grunt as hogs doe, and barke as dogges (according to their cuſtome) to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize the prohibiting of the holy Scripture in the vulgar tongue, in regard of the hurt they pretend to enſue, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reading of it, (whereof I ſhall ſpeake hereafter) and that they may forbeare to transferre their faults on others; endeauouring to confirme and make good the ſaid inhibition with the place of S. <hi>Matthew, chap.</hi> 7. in which Chriſt teacheth vs only thus much, that he would not haue time ſpent, and paines taken in preaching to ſuch of whoſe amendment wee can haue no hope, as <hi>Chryſostome</hi> here expounds it; and this makes no whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reading of holy Scripture in the vulgar tongue, vnleſſe the Pope be ſo euill opinionated of all that are not Clergie men, as to cenſure them all as profligate and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately reprobate; and that in them there is no hope of amendment, and ſo conſequently repute them as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the deuill, and heires of hell: and ſummarily, if the Pope eſteeme them ſuch, he ſhould not onely inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite them the reading of the Bible, but alſo the partaking in the prayers and Sermons of the Church, ſeeing Chriſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6367:23"/>ſpeakes of ſuch. But I doe not beleeue that the moſt holy Father will pronounce ſo hardly of them, for charity will not permit him to doe it, eſpecially of his owne children. For the Father being moſt holy in the ſuperlatiue degree, at leaſt his ſonnes ſhould be holy: and though they were wicked, (as to ſpeake freely the trueth, they are not very good) he therefore ought the rather, not onely permit them, but alſo perſwade them to read it. The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being (as I haue formerly euicted) an vniuerſall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries ſhop, which hath powerfull remedies for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſort of infirmitie and griefe; to what better place can the Pope renuoy ſuch as are enfeebled with the wound of ſinne? For what thing is more proper and fit for a ſicke man, then Phyſicke; and for a wounded man, then that which will heale his wounds? The Pope if he were a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and not a tyrant, ought inſtantly to licence to his ſonnes and the faithfull holy Scripture, and chiefly to thoſe that are faint and weake: for, <hi>hee that is well needes not the Phyſician or Phyſicke, but he that is ſicke.</hi> This is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent;<note place="margin">Torres lib. <hi>25.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> de ſu Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſofia de prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes.</note> and yet that it may be the more cleare, let vs heare what Father <hi>Torres</hi> ſaith on thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 1. Tim. 3. <hi>All Scripture is diuinely inſpired, &amp;c.</hi> After hee hath ſaid that, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſends his diſciple <hi>Timothy</hi> vnto the Scripture, in which he might learne whatſoeuer he ſtood in need of: He further addes, If he ſo earneſtly enioyne a man repleniſhed with the Spirit of grace, the reading of holy Scripture, what would he ſay to one full of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant ſpirit? hee would haue ſaid to ſuch a one, as the Redeemer of the world ſaid to the Scribes and Phariſes, who perceiuing the crudity of their ſtomackes, and that their apoſtumated boſoms could not be mitigated by any lenitiues, he ſent them to the diuine Scriptures, as to a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique hoſpitall for the wounded and maimed, <hi>Search the Scriptures, Ioh.</hi> 5. that they by reading and perpending the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6367:23"/>ſame, might know that he preached all the truth to them. All this ſaith this Author: And the Pope ſhould doe ſo, herein imitating Chriſt our Lord (whoſe Vicar hee ſaith he is, though indeed hee be his enemy) ſeeing Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that his very enemies ſhould ſearch the Scriptures, and examine by them the doctrine he preached to them: and this he did, becauſe he was aſſured, that it helde cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie with them. But the Pope would not haue his doctrine brought to any triall, much leſſe to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of holy Scripture, becauſe hee knowes it to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant thereunto; and therefore in the Countreys ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto his tyrannie, to wit, where the Inquiſition hath place, hee ſuffers none to enquire which is the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which the falſe; but contrariwiſe if any be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to finde out and receiue the trueth, and to this ende ſearch the Scripture, he cauſeth ſuch a one to be burned, and not ſo ſatisfied, doeth further declare all his kinred and allies liuing, and his poſterity to be infamous, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of obtaining offices and dignities of honour and truſt: Though it be certaine, that God would not the ſonne ſhould ſuſtaine the blame of the fathers ſinne, much leſſe bee puniſhed for that wherein his father was not blame-worthy, but rather commendable. But herein, as alſo in the reſt, the Pope is guided by the ſame infernall ſpirit, that the falſe prophet Mahomet is, who well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if his doctrine ſhould be diſputed of, and the trueth debated by good reaſons, of neceſſity the falſeneſſe of it would be deſcried: The firſt thing he commanded was, that vnder paine of death none ſhould be ſo preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, as to canuaſe the ground and trueth of his Law, but rather that his diſciples ſhould be obliged to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it by way of hoſtilitie againſt any that would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it, this precept is fully practiſed in thoſe kingdoms in which the Inquiſition is eſtabliſhed; and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6367:24"/>the Pope would it were in all the world. But refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this to ſome other place, I will cloſe with the ſaying of Doctor <hi>Ylleſcas,</hi> who after he hath recited what is ſaid of <hi>Mahomet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ylleſcas en la hiſtoria Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical. fol. <hi>205.</hi>
                  </note> ſpeaketh as followeth; <hi>Wherein if thoſe who gaue credit vnto him, had not beene ſo blinde, they might haue ſeene that bee was an Impoſtor, ſeeing hee would not haue it controuerted, whether that he taught them were good or euill.</hi> Oh how much I deſire, beloued countreymen, that you would conſider, that for as much as hee conſtraines you to beleeue and holde, whatſoeuer the Church of Rome beleeueth and holdeth, without permitting you to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether it be a true or falſe Church, his ſcope is no other then to deceiue you; and if you be not totally blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, you muſt of neceſſity perceiue it. Looke well vnto it, for it imports and concernes you more then it doeth me, and I diſcharge my duety in admoniſhing you of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, our aduerſaries obiect to vs, that the holy Scripture is obſcure: and that therefore it ſhould bee reſerued from the vulgar. This is a meere lye and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and a manifeſt impietie, becauſe the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (as the Papiſts themſelues preach, and teach) is like an Epiſtle or Letter, that God writes to all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, wherein he expreſſeth his will, and what hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires from euery one. Whereupon it muſt needs follow, that in things which of neceſſity we are to learne out of the ſame, it is moſt cleare and delucidant. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, God had not performed ſo much as his owne part, in that he pretended, which is, to reueale and make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto vs his holy will, which can not be auerred without great blaſphemy. Wherefore, let vs giue eare to the moſt learned Doctor <hi>Leon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leon</hi> en el prologo de los nombres de Chriſto.</note> who with his accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med erudition and learning, confirmes what I haue ſaid, in theſe words he ſpeaking thus: It is a very apparent thing, that the holy Scriptures were inſpired of God,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6367:24"/>that they might be a comfort vnto vs, in the moleſtations and troubles of this life, and in the darkeneſſe and errors of the ſame, a guiding and directing light, and that for the wounds which ſinne and euill paſſions make in our ſoules, we might haue a peculiar and healthfull remedy for euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And becauſe he writ them for this end, which is vniuerſall, it is likewiſe euident, that hee meant the vſe likewiſe of them ſhould bee common to all; and ſo, for his part, he conſtituted and ordayned them, for he writ them in plaine and perſpicuous wordes, and in a tongue that was naturall and vulgar amongſt them, to whom he firſt gaue them:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arinzano</hi> en ſu Roſario, fol, <hi>138.</hi>
                  </note> afterward he appointed that they ſhould be tranſlated into other languages, &amp;c. Father <hi>Arinzano</hi> thought and affirmed as much as <hi>Leon,</hi> though in fewer words; <hi>The holy Scripture</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is a plaine and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Booke without danger, which God gaue vnto vs, that by the ſame we might knowe him.</hi> Doctor <hi>Brauo</hi> ſpeakes with S. <hi>Gregory, that as the looking-glaſſe is a thing which moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brauo,</hi> en la Vigilia Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, fol. <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to life repreſents things to the eye, ſo the Scripture containes all that which any wayes is pertinent for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And he addes, <hi>that holy Scripture is a glaſſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and an information apt and requiſite for all ages,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reinoſa,</hi> en el Maeſtro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano, fol. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for all kinde and manner of people.</hi> Father <hi>Reynoſa</hi> affirmes with the ſame <hi>Gregory, that the holy Scripture, with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurities thereof, exerciſeth the ſtrong and intelligent, and with it's humble phraſe and ſtile, applies it ſelfe to the capacitie of the ſimple, and that it is not ſo intricate, as we neede to feare entring into the ſame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puente</hi> en la guia ſpiritual. fol. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> Father <hi>Puente</hi> is rare and excellent in this point, and firſt he ſayes; <hi>the ſacred and holy Goſpels doe fitte themſelues to all qualities and conditions of men; for as Manna, being but one onely meate, comprehended the ſancur and taſte of all other, and was pleaſing to the reliſh of him that eate it; ſo the word of God, expreſt in the Goſpel, bends it ſelfe to the apprehenſion of the hearers and Readers, yeelding to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6367:25"/>euery one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem ibidem fol. <hi>293.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that ſpirituall refection, which his owne neceſsity and will requires.</hi> In another place hee ſayes againe, with S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> (out of whom hee alſo tooke all the reſt hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered) <hi>In the Sea, or Ocean of the holy Scripture, the Lambe may wade, and the Elephant may ſwimme. Becauſe the ſimpler ſort like Lambes, may there meete with many verities, which they may reade and meditate vpon with ſecuritie, wading through this deepe Ocean by the banke or ſhore, and ſo they of more ſublime wit and apprehenſion ſhall encounter with many deepe myſteries, of ſuch profunditie, that they knowe not where to finde any ground: but they ſhall bee in no danger if they ſwimme with humility, and with a demall of their owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, reuerencing alwayes thoſe ſecrets, that they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and enter into; and thus both the one ſort and the other, with their reading and meditation on the holy Scripture as they ought to doe, ſhall obtaine the ſame fruits and benefites.</hi> Furthermore,<note place="margin">Idem ibidem fol. <hi>394.</hi>
                  </note> this ſelfe ſame Authour, ſpeakes in another place, <hi>That the holy Goſpels are vnto vs eyes wherwith we may diſcerne and vnderſtand the diuine Myſteries, diſtinctly and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly, and without the vaile of Figures, and that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part a reſplendant &amp; ſoueraigne light to thoſe that reade them, reuealing vnto them ſuch things as they are to beleeue, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they are to attend, the puniſhments they ſhould feare, and the ſinnes they ought to ſhunne, and auoid, &amp;c.</hi> Hee alſo ſaies in the ſame place, <hi>That the holy Ghost aſsiſts thoſe that reade and meditate on the holy Scripture, raiſing vp their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and wills, that they may diſcerne loue, and practiſe that which therein is comprehended.</hi> And hereunto hee addes, <hi>That this diuine Spirit opens our apprehenſion in the reading, that in the reading we may vnderſtand: But thoſe that depraue the holy Scipture, alleadging that it is obſcure, and not intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, herein they likewiſe defraud the holy Ghoſt, the Authour thereof; imputing vnto him (O infernall and diabolicall blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie) the note of Imprudence, Impotencie, and ignorance,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6367:25"/>that being willing</hi> (as this Author ſpeakes) <hi>to open the ſence thereof to them that reade it, cannot doe the like to the vulgar ſorte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Obiection of our opoſites, the Papiſts, is, that by the too common reading of the holy Scriptures, many take occaſion to erre, and that therfore they are not to be publiſhed in the vulgar tongue. To this ſo friuolous and common obiection, and calumnie, I firſt anſwere: that the holy Scripture is ſo farre from being a motiue and ouerture to errours, that the ſame rather curbes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serpi</hi> de purgae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio, fol. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and corrects them, as Father <hi>Serpi,</hi> together with <hi>Thomas de Campis</hi> teach; And there is nothing that doth ſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and fortifie our mindes and vnderſtandings againſt errours, as the ſaid peruſall, and reading: As with <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ustinianus,</hi> Frier <hi>Ioſeph de Ieſus Maria</hi> affirmes,<note place="margin">Fr. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> del libro de la caſtidad.</note> and none will doubt of this, but ſuch as haue no ſhame, neither before God nor men. Secondly, I anſwere: that though for our ſinnes there are many who abuſe the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ground and erect their owne errours, yet ought they not for all this to bee prohibited,<note place="margin">Fr. <hi>Leandro de Granada</hi> en el prologo del libro intitulade luz de las ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauiilas.</note> as Father <hi>Gratian</hi> formerly declared vnto vs, and two more do now affirme: The firſt is Father <hi>Leandro de Granada,</hi> in theſe words; No man wil forbeare to miniſter wholſome phyſick, though ſome weake perſon may peraduenture conuert the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine into poiſon. For both God and naturall reaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs vs, that wee ſhould not neglect the great fruit and benefit that may accrew to many by auoiding the deſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate malice of ſome, that put themſelues to death with their owne hands, and blind themſelues becauſe they would not behold the Sunne: for this were a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of that which is good to the good man, to whom properly it belongeth to preuent an euill man, of that ill himſelfe ſeekes. Thus farre the ſame Author proceedes: whereupon he concludes, that though many abuſe the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6367:26"/>booke of the Reuelations of S. <hi>Gertrudis,</hi> and other ſuch like, yet ſhould they not for all this bee prohibited in the vulgar tongue. Now if this reaſon bee of force in ſuch bookes, which are repleniſhed with palpable lies, and moſt impudent blaſphemies, as that is which we former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned of the eſpouſal of <hi>Gertrudis</hi> with Chriſt, and that which enſues of her; that is to ſay, when <hi>Gertrudis</hi> was drawing neer to the hour of her death, Chriſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to her, clothed inglorious garments, the ornaments of an heauenly ſpouſe, accompanied with his bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> Euangeliſt, and an innumerable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, both of men and women Saints, of Celeſtial Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers and inhabitants; and in particular, the reſplendant Armie of virgines, all clothed in white, who for all the day long continued in the Monaſtery; and that in the ſame Monaſtery, the Saints men and women, conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Monkes and Nunnes of the Monaſtery; and that the Lord, comming to the bed of his ſpouſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,<note place="margin">Idem c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo del libro <hi>4.</hi> de la inſinuaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on de la diuina piedad.</note> hee beheld her with an amorous countenance, and ſhewed to her many fauours, and kinde entertainements; and ſhe bent her head to Chriſt, who leaning and reſting himſelfe vpon the bed of the ſicke partie, with both his hands hee opened his breaſt,<note place="margin">The Reader muſt obſerue (as hee may perceiue in the Chap. 36. of the ſame Author) that the ſame was written by the inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt, which promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to them that ſhal reade it, admirable benefits.</note> and manifeſted it to her, and ſayd: I will now free thee, from the bandes of the fleſh, and preſent thee to my ſelfe, as the treaſure and ioy of my heart, to enioy thy ſweete and pleaſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie &amp;c.) Wherefore as I ſaid, if this reaſon bee of force in ſuch like bookes, who can bee ſo ſhameleſſe, as to denie, but that it muſt needes bee much more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualent in the bookes of the holy Scripture, which the holy Ghoſt himſelfe inſpired into his ſeruants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, who writte them to open our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and make them ſacred and holy.</p>
               <p>And now it is time that we come to the other <hi>Granada,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6367:26"/>who as it ſeemes, hath conuerted his ſweet and pleaſant graines, into fearefull and thundring bullets, not ſo pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and mortall to vs, as to the Romane Church it ſelfe: For he applies himſelfe purpoſely, to refute the vanity of that propounded calumnie, with as much vehemency and ſplene, as if his owne life therein concurr'd.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambulo, de la ſegurda parte, de la Introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion del Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo.</note> This Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſayes, how others obiect, that by good reading, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny take an occaſion to runne into many errors: To this I make anſwere, That there is nothing ſo good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfect, which humane malice may not depraue and abuſe. What doctrine can be more exact and infallible, then that of the Goſpels and of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles? and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the heretiques that euer haue beene, both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne, and of ancient times, haue pretended to ground their hereſies vpon this ſo perfect doctrine: whereupon the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> making mention of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, he ſayth, that there are in them many very difficult things to be vnderſtood, ſo that many wicked men tooke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion out of this, to plant their errors. And further hee addes, that heretiques labour to maintaine themſelues, out of all the bookes of the holy Scriptures, wreathing and wreſting them to colour and cloake their errors. And beſides this, what is there in humane life, ſo neceſſary and profitable, but if wee forecaſt ſome inconueniences that may enſue, wee may thinke it fit to be reiected? Thus fathers ſhould neuer marrie their daughters, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiues die in childbed; and other ſome, are cut off by the crueltie of their husbands: let there be no Phyſicke, nor Phyſicians, becauſe many times, both they and their medicines kill: there muſt be no ſwords nor armes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men euery day kill one another: men muſt not croſſe the Seas, in that there happen euery day ſo many ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackes both of men and goods: all ſtudy in Theologie muſt be laid apart, becauſe all heretiques abuſing and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terating
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6367:27"/>of the ſame, take occaſion to ground their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and errors thereupon. But what do I ſpeake of earthly things, ſeeing euen thoſe heauenly are not exempted from their inconueniences? What can be more expedient and requiſite for the vſe and gouernment of this world, then the Sunne? and yet how many men haue dyed &amp; growen ſicke, through the immoderate heate thereof? But why doe I inſiſt in theſe things? when euen from the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, mercy, and paſſion of Ieſues Chriſt our Sauiour, (which are the fundamentall cauſes of all our happineſſe) euill men preſume to perſeuere and continue in their ſins? Vnto all that, formerly deliuered, I will annexe this one thing of great conſideration; and therefore I demand, What more efficacious and piercing motiue can there be, to conuince all vnderſtanding, and reduce them to true faith, then the reſurrection of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who had lien bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried foure dayes, and ſtunke, whom the Lord raiſed vp againe with theſe words; <hi>Lazarus come foorth.</hi> And this was ſufficient, that neither the gates of death, nor the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; bands wherewith he was bound, could keepe him in his graue. What heart can there be ſo hard and obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that will not be mollified, and yeeld to the faith and beliefe of that Lord, by meanes of this ſo inexplicable a miracle? But O the incredible malice of humane hearts! this ſo wonderfull a miracle is not onely not preualent, to ſubdue the hearts of the high Prieſts and Phariſes, but further here-from, they were excited to condemne to death the worker of ſo renowmed a miracle: wherewith not being content, they ſought to kill <hi>Lazarus,</hi> becauſe many by his meanes came to beleeue in the Sauiour. Wherefore, if humane malice be ſo implacable, as that it here-from aſſum'd a motiue and ſtimulation to ſo great a wickedneſſe, who can produce any argument from that abuſe, wherewith wicked men alienate and adulterate
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6367:27"/>good things, wringing and wreſting them to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and prophane willes, that hereby a good ſhould be preuented and cut off? To this demaund made by ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous an Author, (whoſe reaſons all theſe I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, were) I would faine haue the Romane Antichriſt make anſwere, who prohibites the reading of the ſacred Scriptures to an innumerable ſort of the vulgar, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them hereby, of infinite many benefits, which from the reading of the ſame doe accrew, in that ſome abuſe and alienate them. This Author ſtill proſecutes, let all this be ſpoken, that men may diſcerne and vnderſtand, that there can be nothing ſo good, but it is expoſed to ſome inconueniences, yet procur'd rather by the abuſes of men, then out of the originall nature and qualitie of things. And yet for all this, there is no reaſon, that through the diſorder and miſpriſion of a few, many and good men ſhould looſe the fruit and emolument of wholeſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. All which our bleſſed Sauiour plainely intimated vnto vs, in the parable of the Cockle, where he ſayes,<note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that the other ſeruants demanding of their maſter, whether they ſhould weed out the bad weeds or no, that ſo they might not be preiudiciall to the good ſeed, hee anſwered them, that they ſhould let them alone, becauſe it may well be, that in plucking vp the weeds, together with the, they might irradicate the good eares. In which parable hee points out vnto vs, that the priuiledge and immunities of the good ought ſo tenderly to be reſerued, that many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities are to be digeſted, rather then that good men ſhould be hurt or damnified. If Chriſt himſelfe taught vs thus much, why does the Pope, who vaunts himſelfe to be his Vicar, both teach and practiſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? Why doeth hee depriue good men of the diuine Scriptures, and therein of a treaſure ineſtimable, in that ſome particular bad men vſe them ill? ſeeing he is not a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6367:28"/>vice god vpon earth, (as with a braſen face hee entitles himſelfe) but a vice-deuill of hell, whoſe workes he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes, and whom men obey in euery thing; whereof (except he ſpeedily repent) hee ſhall one day receiue the iuſt reward and recompence. But yet, let vs proceede a little further with this Author: Vnto all this I adde (ſaith hee) that ſound doctrine is ſo farre from being a motiue and ſtimulation vnto errour, that rather it is the meanes to confirme and ſtrengthen vs in our faith: wherefore I thought good, here to inſert a thing, which a certaine Lord of the holy Inquiſition of theſe kingdomes of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> related to me, the which is very behoouefull to prooue the benefit of good and diſcreet reading, and the diſcommoditie that growes from bad and iniudiciall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing of bookes. This Lord therefore, reported to mee, that a man came to that ſacred Court, to require mercy, who freely confeſt, that applying himſelfe to reade cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and vicious bookes, his true faith was thereby ſo ſhaken, as that he firmely beleeued hee had no more to anſwere for, but to die like a beaſt. But afterwards, vpon a ſpeciall occaſion that fell out, or rather in that it was ſo ordained by diuine prouidence, he began againe to reade and peruſe books of good inſtruction; by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he was releaſed of the blindneſſe wherein he formerly ſtood. This very Author ſtill annexeth another exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a Moore, whoſe eyes God opened by the helpe of good and commendable reading, euen as it happened to the Queene of Ethiopia's Eunuch, by reading in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſaias.</hi> Wherefore if the benefites growing from good reading be ſo diuine, and that of corrupt and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reading, ſo hurtfull and pernicious, let me aske of the Papiſts one queſtion; From whence comes it, that bad reading is permitted to all in generall, and the good onely to a few in number? If they know and beleeue that the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6367:28"/>Eunuch, being one in the ranke of ſecular men, attain'd to the vnderſtanding of Chriſtian veritie, by reading of the holy Scriptures, and that the fore-mentioned Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, by the reading of profane bookes loſt his faith, and became an Atheiſt, how comes it, that the Lords Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors after hereticall errors, doe not conſent that there one onely booke of the diuine Scriptures may be publiſht in the vulgar tongue, that ſo ſecular men, like to that Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, may daily reade in it, whereas they tolerate an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite company of obſcene and vicious bookes, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to come into euery mans hands? If they take away the holy Scriptures from the popular ſort, which might be very profitable for many, and no preiudice to any, (except they aſſume it from their owne corruption and blindneſſe) vnder colour and pretext, that ſome ground their errors out of them, how is it, that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo many bad and profane bookes, that can benefite none, but (as experience continually teacheth) are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of many euils? I cannot conceiue what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the Papiſts will returne hereunto: but this I am aſſured of, that as the Pope, the Inquiſitors, and great Prelats know well, that the vulgar ſort can neuer poſſibly come to the ſenſe and feeling of that miſerable ſeruitude, whereunto they haue reduced them, by the meanes of depraued and petulant bookes, they therefore indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently permit them to be read of all men, making no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the errors and vices, that encreaſe through the reading of ſuch bookes, in that they ſpeake not againſt the Authoritie of the Pope nor of the Inquiſitors: But by reaſon they know, that the holy Scripture is a cleare and manifeſt light, that will reueale their workes and falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they vſe all the care and circumſpection poſſible, that the vulgar ſort may not reade them, and ſo come to diſcerne the inſupportable yoke they haue laide vpon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6367:29"/>them. This, out of all doubt is the true reaſon, why they ſuppreſſe the reading of holy Scriptures, and tolerate thoſe that are corrupt and bad.</p>
               <p>And that this may the more clearely appeare, I thought fit here to ſet downe ſomewhat of much, which diuers Spaniſh Doctors haue vtter'd againſt prophane bookes, and the great preiudice that euery day growes in <hi>Spaine,</hi> by the reading of them. Father <hi>Torres,</hi> amongſt other things affirmes,<note place="margin">Torres, en la Filoſofia de principes. pag <hi>943.</hi>
                  </note> that many of thoſe bookes vſually read at this day throughout all <hi>Spaine,</hi> are obſcene and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and are good for nothing elſe, but to make Pandors and ſecret Bawdes, teaching them to ſinne, and to ſend many ſoules into hell. Theſe pernicious bookes haue a number of followers and well-willers; but good writings that treat of vertue and pietie, he cloſe hid vp in corners: for theſe ill bookes, like a canker, enter and ſeaze vpon all parts of the mind, and ſo irradicate and plucke vp the root and ground of all vertues; but the Lords Inquiſitors winke at all this. Father <hi>Ioſeph de Ieſus Maria,</hi> is very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable vpon this ſubiect,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fr. Ioſeph</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> del lib. de la caſtidad.</note> exhibiting vnto vs many ſtrong and vnanſwerable reaſons, wherewith to ſubdue and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome our aduerſaries: Firſt of all therefore hee ſayes, that in many bookes, which are much read in the vulgar tongue, and come into the hands of the common people in <hi>Spaine,</hi> they vſe idolatrous ſpeeches and phraſes, wherein the Chriſtian Faith and Religion is ſcandaliz'd, and the religious and godly cuſtomes of Catholike peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: That bookes of Poetrie, are full of blaſphemies, and vent more error, then euer the Gentiles did in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. All this, the ſame Author affirmes, and daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhewes no leſſe, which the Lords Inquiſitors know well enough; and yet notwithſtanding all this, they permit vnto all, and except none, the reading of ſuch bookes: but to reade the word of God in ſecular men,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6367:29"/>they repute it for a crime worthy of death, and as an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that nature, they puniſh it. This very Author ſayes further, That in thoſe bookes there are not onely found many violent inſtigations to vice, but alſo maſters and skilfull pedagogues, who teach and inſtruct, how to attempt and proſecute them; yea which is more, they make a bed for hereſies. But this laſt (though it be infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly true) he confirmes with a very groſſe and explodible lie, ſpeaking thus: When impious <hi>Luther</hi> (ſaith hee) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſperſe his poyſon in <hi>Germanie,</hi> Sathan being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to bring into <hi>France</hi> likewiſe this hereſie, when he found ſo maine a reſiſtance in that moſt Chriſtian king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he laboured with ſubtill policie, to haue the Fables of <hi>Amadis</hi> of <hi>Gaule</hi> tranſlated into French, that they might infect and taint the minds of Noble people, they being beſt read, and moſt curious in reading, and to prepare them for the embracing of hereſies; and ſo by the tickling delight of laſciuious loues, of fabulous feats of Armes, and magicall Incantations, the mindes of men in a ſmall time were ſo poiſoned and defiled, that no diſcourſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among ingenious and curious people but of matters ridiculous and fabulous. And that when the deuils mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters perceiued, how this Tranſlation was ſo well recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and entertained, they returne againe, to ſow abroad other dreames and Fables, tranſlating daily more immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and fabulous bookes, which did ſo obfuſcate and darken young wits, and ſo notably polluted and ſtained their willes, that men retir'd themſelues from the reading of good books, and diuine Hiſtories, and euen the Name of Chriſt came to be leſſe called vpon. Thus farre extend the words of that Author; wherein, firſt, matter is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to vs of no ſlender laughter, in his imputing to the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> (whom hee calls heretickes) that which iuſtly at this day may be rather impoſed on the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6367:30"/>Papiſts, and thoſe practiſes currant and in vſe amongſt them, as the ſame Author himſelfe complaines, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with many others, and dayly proofes and trials would informe vs, though they had beene ſilent. For who is ignorant, that in the Papacie, diuine Hiſtories are exil'd and baniſht, and prophane, and fabulous Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces brought in, in their ſtead? No man there, mentions the calling on the Name of Chriſt, but vpon ſome image of ſtone, or wood, of his Mother, or ſome other Saint. And who knowes not, that throughout all the reformed Churches, they are conuerſant generally in reading free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the holy Scriptures, and that onely the ſacred Name of Chriſt is in euery place, and of all men called vpon; and therefore in this reſpect, the Pope, and the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, proſecute them with fire and ſword, endeauouring that thoſe Saints by them canoniz'd, ſhould bee prayed vnto, and Chriſts holy Name quite and cleane forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? But leauing this for another place, let it be lawfull for vs once more, to demand of the Papiſts, What is the reaſon, that they vnderſtanding how theſe fantaſticall and idle bookes, brought ſo much detriment and hurt to the faithfull in <hi>France,</hi> that as wiſe men (whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie it is, as wee ſay in our Spaniſh tongue, <hi>Eſcarmentar en cabeca agena,</hi> To bee afraid by other mens harmes) they doe not baniſh out of the Papacie, the originall and cauſe of ſo many euils, yet this they not onely not doe, but euery day they bring in and multiply theſe brutiſh and ſordide bookes? For labouring ſo induſtriouſly and ſtudiouſly, to remooue out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the vulgar tongue, the ſame being reuealed by God, neither conteining ſo much as one letter, that iuſtly demerits either blame or reprehenſion, but being written onely and wholly for our inſtruction and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite: wherefore, I ſay, vſing ſuch rigor and ſeueritie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6367:30"/>to this diuine Booke, doe they indifferently and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally permit all men, to reade an infinite number of baſe and pernicious bookes, repleniſht and ſtufft with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheraies, and implying many Hereſies, whereunto they attract, and drawe the moſt godly and zealous, as our Aduerſaries themſelues frankly confeſſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. Till our Aduerſaries giue a full anſwere to this demand, it will not bee altogether vnfit, here to ſet downe, what learned Doctor <hi>Leon</hi> ſaith, after hee hath complained, that one of the greateſt calamities of our times, was, that men are growen to ſuch an inclination and diſpoſition, (hee ſpeakes of the Papiſts, and more particularly of the Spaniards) that the holy Scriptures, which at other times, were wont to be a cure and remedy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leon</hi> en el prologo de lot nombres de Chriſto.</note> are become an infectious poyſon, for this preiudice (he ſayes) they haue wrought, that by the preſumption and pride of the vulgar, they haue made the reading of the Scriptures vnprofitable for them, and ſo another diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie enſues, I cannot tell whether I may iuſtly ſay a worſer, for they betake themſelues, without any bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or reſtraint, to the reading of many bookes, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaine, and friuoulous, but importantly obnoxious and hurtfull; the which as by the Art of the deuill, haue in number encreaſt more in our age then any other, for want of ſuch as were good and vertuous, and the ſame hath happened to vs, as many times it doth with the earth, which, when it cannot bring forth corne, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth thornes; and I affirme, that this ſecond dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, doth in ſome ſort ſurmount the other, becauſe in the ſacred Scriptures, men onely loſe a great Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and meanes, to be good, but in theſe profane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors they finde the occaſions, to be euill and wicked, for in the firſt onely the Rudder and Sterne of good gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken away, and in the other fomentation and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6367:31"/>nouriſhment is exhibited to vices. For as <hi>S. Paul</hi> allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, euill wordes corrupt good manners, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene and vnpure booke, which is dayly before the eyes of him that reades it, what will it not effect? or how is it poſſible hee ſhould bee cleare from groſſe and vnwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e blood, that is maintained with nothing but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and poyſon. And in trueth, if wee doe but intentiuely obſerue it, and bee iuſt and vpright iudges, wee cannot but giue ſentence, that the greateſt part of our deprau'd and debauſht cuſtomes (which wee dayly ſee and meete withall) proceedes from the continuall reading of theſe profane and ſcurrillous bookes, with a reliſh of Gentiliſme and Inſidelitie, which thoſe that are Zealous of Gods ſeruice finde in them, and I knowe not, whether in any age amongſt Chriſtian people, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plague hath been prooued. In my iudgement, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the roote, and the abſolute originall of theſe euils, conſiſts in theſe bookes. This and much more, the ſame famous Doctor writ vpon this particular, and queſtionleſſe would haue ſpoken much more, and farre more ſignificantly, had it not been for that ſame cruell, barbarous, and inhumane Inquiſition of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in which moſt ſtinking and obſcure priſon, hee remained ſeuen yeeres, in the Towne of <hi>Valladolid,</hi> where (as all the world knowes) hee vnderwent great troubles, affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and torments, becauſe hee vttered in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a Propoſition, that was not pleaſing to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> though it was but Chriſtian and true, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, peraduenture wee will intreate more at large in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke. Now, it remaines, we only obſerue how the ſacred Scriptures are not prohibited the faithfull, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them within a certaine moderation and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe this impertinent and ſeuere prohibition (as the Papiſts themſelues well knowe) is a cauſe, of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6367:31"/>greater and more pernicious Inconueniences. And who can bee ſo credulous as to beleeue, that to make bad men good, they muſt needes depriue them of the holy Bible, which is the onely Inſtrument to make them good? when they freely permit diſhoneſt and immodeſt bookes, which are the proper Inſtruments of ſinne and impietie? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee cannot but bee a foole that beleeues this. But let vs grant, that they who tooke from the vulgar the vſe and reading of the Scriptures, pretended herein to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue occaſion and meanes of breeding errours; yet, when long experience had taught them, that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inci erunt in scillam cupientes vitare Caribdim:</hi> which is, that ſtudying to preuent one preiudice, they brought in a thouſand, (ſeeing through default of the holy Scriptures, profane bookes crept in) why, I ſay,<note place="margin">Dato vno ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdo miltae ſequuntur.</note> did they not labour to ſuppreſſe ſo pernicious a p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ague, by reſtoring them, and excluding the other, ſeeing naturall reaſon informes vs, that of two neceſſary euils, we ſhould euer imbrace the leaſt: how much more in that the holy Scriptures are good of themſelues, and remote from all euill. There is no doubt, but if that prohibition ſimply aymed at the good and benefit of the faithful, they would haue beene ſo; but there's all the matter, in that they do not ſo much ſeeke the profit and benefit of the faithfull, but rather their owne particular ends and intereſts; the which conſiſts mainely, inconcealing from the people the knowledge of trueth, which they might attayne vnto by meanes of the holy Scriptures, and that they ſhould not ſeeke and affect to vnderſtand it, they haue alwayes entertained them, with the ſcumme and dregges of idle and profane bookes: the reading whereof is not onely frankely permitted them, but further it is a cauſe, that oppoſite to the willes and deſires of good men, they are peruſed and read ouer by all; of which, amongſt others,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6367:32"/>the former mentioned Father <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> complaines in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Fr. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ibid. fol. <hi>796.</hi>
                  </note> The abuſiue and poyſonable practiſe of euill bookes, allowed of in <hi>Spaine,</hi> from whence the greateſt part of corrupt cuſtomes proceedes, comes not from the allowance and toleration of the Lawes, nor from the King, becauſe they haue ordained ſufficient remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this dammage and preiudice, but rather from the negligence and careleſneſſe of Iudges, both Secular and Eccleſiaſticall, in executing ſuch iuſt and good Lawes, and they, whom this moſt of all did concerne, were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prelats of the Church, who being to giue dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice hereof to Kings and temporal Lords, that they might helpe and ioyne together, for the baniſhing out of the Commonwealth theſe fountains of pollution and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe; they did not only not do it, but Kings &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exhorting them to purge and cleanſe the Kingdome of this letiferous poyſon, they yet liue, and perſeuere in the ſame, with moſt pernicious careleſneſſe and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, not with out ſpeciall and ſingular danger to their owne conſciences, and the ſoules of their poore ſubiects. A little after, the ſame Authour ſayes, it is a lamentable pitie, that ſo many ſage and wiſe conſiderations hauing bene entred into, to eſtabliſh theſe iuſt Lawes, which was (to remooue out of their Studies, and Libraries theſe hurtfull bookes) ſo many Petitions preferred by the Sollicitors of the Kingdome, ſo many meetings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations with the Lords of the Counſell, with ſuch a number of manifeſtations written and publiſhed, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kinggs pleaſure in this behalfe, it could neuer bee once put in execution, the vrgent neceſſitie of this exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution being ſo materiall and important, what ſhall wee ſay to this? but onely, that the Pope, Biſhops, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Faith, conniue at this perdition, ſeeing neither the King, nor the whole Kingdome can ſo far preuaile
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6367:32"/>with them, as to execute ſuch iuſt, behoofefull and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall Lawes; in all other reſpects they being ſo ſedulous, induſtrious and circumſpect in purging (as they ſay) the bookes and writings of the holy Doctors of the Church, (not exempting herein the Scriptures diuine) as appeares in a publiſht booke, called <hi>Index expurgatorius.</hi> All this wee haue produced, by reaſon of that, which Father <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada</hi> ſayes, he heard from an Inquiſitor, and hee himſelfe alleadgeth it, to ſhew the great dammage that proceedes from bookes of corrupt doctrine and inſtruction, and the inexplicable emolument &amp; profit, deriuing from bookes of good and vertuous Argument; it now remaines that we ſhould conclude and ſhut vp this diſcourſe, with the very words which the ſame <hi>Granada</hi> vſeth, in the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his diſcourſe: Lawes, and iuſt Tribunalls, looke not ſo much vpon particulars as to generalls, that is to ſay, not what may happen to particular perſons, but what generally concerneth the good of all, who, in no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to periſh, through the abuſe and diſorder of ſome, neither in like manner doe they aime, at the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular preiudice which things procure, if the generall benefits bee greater then the preiudices: as we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in Nauigation at Sea, for if the dammages of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke be great and important yet the benefits of Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation are farre greater.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the principall reaſons which our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries produce, againſt the publicke vſe and reading of the holy Scriptures, the reſt are ſo weake and friuolous, as they deſerue not to haue any more time ſpent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding them, for that would bee as much as to refute them; and ſo the time wee ſhould ſpend in them, will be better gain'd, in ſetting downe two reaſons, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the other before alleadged, ſhew plainely to our view, and as it were with the pointing of a finger, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6367:33"/>the Pope depriues not the vulgar of the Bible, to doe them good, but rather to auoyd and ſhunne his owne precipice, with which wee will cloſe and ſhut vp this Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt reaſon is, becauſe (as Father <hi>Luys de Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> ſayes) all the ſtudie and care of our capitall enemie is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Granada</hi> en el preambulo de la <hi>2.</hi> parte de la introduceion del Symbole.</note> to bereaue vs of this light of the word of God, and hee confirmes it thus: The firſt thing the Philiſtines per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, when they had <hi>Sampſon</hi> in their power, was to plucke out his eyes; and when they had done this, they found no difficultie in doing whatſoeuer elſe they meant to lay vpon him, euen to the making of him grinde in a Mill. And this Authour addes, of the ſame people it is written, that they were very carefull and vigilant to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that there might bee no Forges amongſt the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but that hauing neede of any ſuch things, they ſhould repaire vnto their Countrey to haue them, and to make vſe of their Forges, becauſe the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by this meanes, remaining vnfurniſhed and diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, they might the more eaſily ſuppreſſe and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them. With the ſame Authour therefore, wee may demaund, what bee the Armes of a Chriſtian war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, but the Word of God? and ſtill with the ſame Authour wee perſeuere and ſay; our enemies in many parts, haue ſtript and bereaued vs of theſe Armes, and in ſtead of them, left vnto vs the bookes of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and malice, which are obſcene and profane bookes, inſtigators vnto vice, all which they doe, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hereby remayning diſarmed, they might ceaze vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and diſpoſe of them and their occaſions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne willes and pleaſures, imitating herein, that ſacrilegious and abominable King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who commanded the bookes of Gods Law, to be torne in pieces, and burnt; and to kill any one, in whoſe hands
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6367:33"/>at any time they were found.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pacheco</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſcurſos, fol. <hi>732.</hi>
                  </note> This he did, becauſe (as Father <hi>Pacheco</hi> obſerues) the wicked man ſaw, that for his wicked deſſignes and intentions, it was a behoofe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing, to extinguſh and ſuppreſſe the ſacred bookes: And this, and no other, is the liuely reaſon, why the Pope and the Inquiſitors ſo expreſly prohibit them, and take away the liues of ſuch faithfull men, that deſire to reade them in their owne tongue: like another <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>This Lye you may reade in</hi> Fonſeca, en la ſegunda parte del tratado del amor de Dios, cap. <hi>2. and in</hi> fr. Luys de Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada, en el preambulo, de la <hi>2.</hi> parte de la introduccion.</note> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as hee did, which moſt impudently and falſely they would put vpon, and applie vnto <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, King of <hi>England;</hi> affirming that hee tooke from religious men the holy Bookes, knowing that the reading of them was as powerfull and trenchant Armes. Vndoubtedly, if I ſhall expreſſe what I haue by experience found true, in this moſt noble and flouriſhing Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> about this particular, it will bee wonderfull different, and contrary to that which we ſee dayly practiſed at this day, in all gouernments liuing vnder the obedience of the Romane Church; For whereas there, vpon grieuous and cruell penalties, the common people are prohibited the reading of the ſacred Scriptures, becauſe the Pope, and the reſt of the Prelates know well that they would finde matter enough in them, wherewith to conuince and condemne, their falſe doctrines, here all faithfull and Chriſtian men, are exhorted to reade and meditate on them; nay, they are ſharpely rebuked if they doe not ſo: For here neither the Biſhops, nor other Prelates and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church haue any feare, leaſt the people ſhould finde their condemnation, whereas in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, this Diuine light of the holy Bookes is baniſht, as Father <hi>Granada</hi> complaynes and laments;<note place="margin">Granada <hi>ibid:</hi>
                  </note> but in this Realme it ſhines and lightens in the moſt hidden and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecret corners thereof. There Prelates are deſtitute of all knowledge, yea, in ſo groſſe a manner, as that ſome of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6367:34"/>them neuer ſo much as ſawe the Bible,<note place="margin">en c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> as Father <hi>Eſtella</hi> complaines, but here there is ſcant a childe of a dozen yeeres olde, who hath not read and read it often. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kingdomes, many of the Paſtours doe not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Diuine writings, and which is more, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne them, or at leaſt ſeeme to make of them but a light and ſlender eſteeme, neither doe they retaine any good opinion of thoſe that doe vnderſtand them, as moſt learned Doctor <hi>Leon</hi> affirmes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leon</hi> enel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lego, de los nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres de Chriſto.</note> Here, all Paſtors in generall, but eſpecially the moſt reuerend Biſhops, are verie conuerſant in the ſame ſtudie of Diuine bookes, euery one highly eſteeming, to ſtudie and vnderſtand them, and hee is reputed but a bad Chriſtian, and a worſe Paſtour that doeth otherwiſe. And finally, in thoſe parts, like wicked <hi>Antiochus,</hi> they put thoſe Seculars to death that read the holy Scripture: but here like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and zealous Chriſtians, they commend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerate ſuch as reade them. This, becauſe it is well knowne to all, I doe not here particularly ſpecifie in any large relation, becauſe experience hath taught mee the trueth thereof. From whence I gather, that what the Papiſts faigne and deuiſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall lye, forged by themſelues; for how can it ſtand with any reaſon, that to bring in a Religion, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooues nothing more in the faithfull, then the reading of the holy Scriptures, <hi>Henry</hi> the eight ſhould prohibite them, and therefore what they falſely father vpon <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, rather may bee applied to the Romane Church, where the Scriptures are forbidden vpon paine of death, for no other ende, but the ſame for which <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great, ſuppreſt and forbade the Booke of God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon which ſheweth that the Pope for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth the Scriptures, not ſo much for the peoples good
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6367:34"/>as to ſhunne his owne ſhame, is this enſuing. The Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> knowing, that it hath euer beene a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtome in the Chriſtian Church, that publike Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhould daily impart to all the people, the reading of the Prophets and other bookes of the holy Scripture, and that in a Tongue which they vnderſtood, (as may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon the fourth Chapter to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Sandoual</hi> well notes it,<note place="margin">Sandonal en il tratado delofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtico, pag. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> as wee ſhall ſhew by and by) and withall perceiuing on the one part, that he could not quite put downe this good cuſtome, and without apparent ſcandall; and on the other ſide, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that if the reading of the Scripture were conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to be permitted in the vulgar tongue, his tyrannicall Empire would ſoone fall to the ground, (becauſe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that one ſhould reade, or heare read the holy Scripture, but he muſt diſcerne the falſhood of the Popes doctrine) hereupon hee craftily deuiſed a middle way to effect his purpoſe, which was (as wee haue ſaid) princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to conceale his owne ſhame, more then to effect the good of the people. Firſt, hee ordained indeed that the Scripture ſhould be read to the people, and thus farre hee cunningly cumplied with the ancient Chriſtian Church, and by this meanes ſubtilly caſt a vaile and miſt ouer his treacherie: but ſecondly, hee ſo ordained reading of the Scripture, with ſuch a limitation and checke, that in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (though the vulgar cannot diſcerne it) hee vtterly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowes the practiſe of the ancient Chriſtian Church, while he reſtraines the reading of it to a tongue not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood vulgarly, that is, to the Latine onely: which, what is it elſe in effect, then not to haue it read at all? and if ſo, it is then moſt apparent, that the peoples vnderſtandings are depriued of an inualuable benefit; and it is not likely that all this buſineſſe ſhould be made for benefit to no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: and if to any body, either to the people, or himſelfe;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6367:35"/>not to the people (as hath beene ſhewed) <hi>ergo,</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and what that is, appeares clearely, though he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to keepe it in the darke, which may beſt be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in a tongue not vnderſtood: but ſuch is the Popes ſubtiltie herein, that the poore ſeduced people cannot ſuſpect him all this while, nor conſequently complaine or ſeeke for remedy, becauſe the Pope ſtill beares them in hand with faire pretenſions, that he ſtill keepes the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome of the Church on foot, though indeed hee doeth nothing leſſe; for the ancient Church euer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Scriptures to the common people, in a tongue knowen and vnderſtood of all, as is euidently prooued by theſe enſuing wordes of <hi>Sandouall. Iuſtinus Martyr</hi> (ſayth hee) relates of the Chriſtians of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church,<note place="margin">Idem. pag. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> that on the Lords day they aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Lectures were read vnto them out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles; and when the Lection was ended, the Paſtor admoniſhed them, to performe in life and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, what they had heard read: whereupon it is more then probable, that the ſaid Lecture and Reading was in the vulgar tongue, well vnderſtood of all the Auditorie; for otherwiſe, the Paſtor ſhould haue beene but a foole, in vrging them to performe, what they neither conceiued nor vnderſtood; becauſe, according to that Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Axiome, <hi>Nihil volutum, quin praecognitum.</hi> Father <hi>Franciſco Antonio</hi> alſo confeſſeth as much,<note place="margin">El Pa. Franciſco Antonio, fol. <hi>91.</hi> de ſus conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raciones ſobre los myſterios de la miſſa.</note> and that in plainer termes and words, as in theſe following: The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of the Apoſtles were read in the preſence and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all the faithfull, ſo as they might be heard not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the learned, but alſo by the vulgar; not onely by olde men, but alſo by young. Then which, what could be ſpoken more plainly? and indeed it doth ſo farre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince the conſciences of the Romaniſts, that as you ſee, they cannot chooſe but confeſſe it, and therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6367:35"/>the Papiſts at this day (that they might ſeeme to continue the ancient cuſtome) not being altogether ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent as altogether to abrogate it, they make pretenſes (but all are but deceitfull ſhadowes) and teach that in the Lectures and Readings of the holy Scriptures in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day, all the people ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, euen as Father <hi>Marquez</hi> clearly confeſſeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marquez</hi> en el reſoro de igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, f. l. <hi>219.</hi>
                  </note> in theſe wordes: One of the principalleſt reaſons, why wee are commanded to heare Maſſe on Feſtiuall dayes, is, becauſe in the Epiſtles, Goſpels, prayers, and other things vttered in the Maſſe, mention is made of all the chiefeſt my ſteries of our Redemption, becauſe faithfull men hearing them, they might be committed to their memories, and they not grow forgetfull of ſuch benefits. This is taken out of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Marquez.</hi> Now if it be true (as is confeſt and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) that the people ſhould commit to memory, and not forget the things they heare, how comes it to paſſe that they doe not ſo? Is it not becauſe they vnderſtand not? and is not the cauſe hereof, their hearing it in an vnknown tongue? and doth not this cut off all the benefits preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and leaue the people in the ſame caſe as if they had no Scriptures at all? For as reaſon informes vs, and that great learned Doctor <hi>Ledeſma</hi> teacheth vs,<note place="margin">Fr. <hi>Pedro de Ledeſma</hi> enel tratado <hi>1.</hi> de laſe christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, eap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> He that can vtter a thing in Latine, if he vnderſtand not the Latine, it is the ſame as if he knew it not at all. Wherefore in the Readings of the Romane Church, it is onely pretended, and no more, that the people vnderſtand: but if you aske them what, or how they vnderſtand, their laſt refuge and all the anſwere that is left is, That they vnderſtand what the Church doth, and that implicitly. Moreouer, for the better preuailing of this deluſion, and the entertainment of this pretenſe, the Papiſts themſelues beleeue, that in the Maſſe Chriſt preacheth vnto them his Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aluarado</hi> en ſu arte de oien viuir, lib. <hi>40.3.</hi>
                  </note> by the mouth of the Prieſt, as <hi>Aluarado</hi> notes, and alſo by the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6367:36"/>mouth of the Deacon, in the ſame, which they call the high Maſſe, as the <hi>Gloſſe</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>ſuper caput perlectis,</hi> 25. <hi>de in ſanctam</hi> 29.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rodriguez</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>101.</hi> deſus obras morales.</note> which Maſter <hi>Rodriguez</hi> alledgeth, who teacheth the ſame. The Papiſts doe likewiſe teach, that the Epiſtle deliuered in the Maſſe, is like vnto a letter, which God ſends vnto men, to reueale vnto them his will, and what hee requires at their hands, and that the Deacon when he reads the Letter, or the Prieſt when hee reads it in the Maſſe, finds the whole will of God therein implyed and intimated,<note place="margin">Puente 4. <hi>tom. fol.</hi> 234.</note> as Father <hi>Puente</hi> ſpeakes. And moreouer <hi>Puente</hi> annexeth, that this is after the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">2. Eſdr. 8.</note> as in the booke of <hi>Eſdras</hi> is expreſſed, that the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, <hi>Legerunt in libro Legis Dei diſtinctè, &amp; apertè ad intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum: &amp; intellexerunt cum legeretur.</hi> If this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I would faine haue the Papiſts themſelues anſwere me; To what end ſhould Chriſt preach his Goſpel vnto men, but to the end they might vnderſtand? for there is no reaſon to ſpeake, when that which is deliuered and ſpoken is not apprehended nor vnderſtood. As S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tena</hi> in Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog. in totam ſacr. Serip. fol. <hi>318.</hi>
                  </note> and conformable to him, the Biſhop of <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſa;</hi> The reaſon hereof themſelues doe yeeld: <hi>quia non prodeſt locutionis integritas, quam non ſequitur, intellectus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis.</hi> And Chriſt our Lord, ſpeaking of a propheſie in theſe words; <hi>qui legit, intelligat:</hi> for if he couet not to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, his reading will be to ſmall purpoſe, as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Puente</hi> notes,<note place="margin">Puente <hi>ibid. fol.</hi> 578.</note> and obſerues. And how is it probable, that Chriſt ſhould intimate and declare vnto them his will, by meanes of the Epiſtle, when they vnderſtand not, what is therein comprehended. This, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, is rather a breathing into the aire, then an inſtructing of the people. It is (as we vſually ſay in our Spaniſh tongue) <hi>predicar en deſierto;</hi> to preach in the deſert: For as the precedent Biſhop alleadged ſayes, this comes to paſſe, when either that which is deliuered is not vnderſtood,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6367:36"/>or that doctrine which is preached, is not obeyed. This is not a manifeſting of Gods will vnto men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tena</hi> in geg. in tota. Scrip. ſacr. fol. <hi>320.</hi>
                  </note> by the mouth of the Prieſt, but a ſpeaking of the Prieſt onely to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, (if ſo be the Prieſt vnderſtand what himſelfe reades, otherwiſe no;) becauſe, as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>qui lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur lingua ignota, non hominibus, ſed Deo loquitur: Deo, quia intelligit eum, non hominibus qui non percipiunt eum:</hi> as the ſaid Biſhop notes very well, vpon that ſame very place of the Apoſtle: conformable to whom,<note place="margin">Tena, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> Father <hi>Hurtado</hi> prooues, and preacheth, <hi>quòd, quando quis Verba facit, apud hominem ignorantem, ſuae linguae, propriè loquendo non loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> the reaſon hereof is, <hi>quia actualis loquutio, eſt actualis ſignificatio rei, &amp; expreſsio, non eſt autem actualis ſignificatio ſine actuali perceptione audientis:</hi> and hee confirmes it by this example, <hi>quia ramus appenſus, non ſignificat aliquid actu, niſi quando, actu ex illo cognito, deuenitur in cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Vini: nec ramus eſt ſignum iumento, ſed potatori.</hi> From all this heretofore expreſſed, I collect, that the Pope, more through force and feare, then conſent or will, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Scriptures in the Church to the people; and this he doeth in Latine, to the end they may not conceiue and vnderſtand them. Wherein he goes quite contrary to the order and courſe helde in the Primitiue Church, before he began to exerciſe his tyrannies vpon men; which ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry order of the Primitiue Church, is now obſeru'd in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and throughout all the Reformed Churches, both conformable to reaſon, the Commandements of God, and Apoſtolicall inſtruction, which already we haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently prooued, and will doe more at large, if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me, in another place.</p>
               <p>Out of all this formerly produced, I conclude, that the Pope forbids the holy Bible to the common people, not ſo much to reprehend them within the bounds of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, as to retaine them in groſſe and palpable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6367:37"/>not to preuent errors in the faithfull, as to nouriſh and maintaine his owne; not to beneſite ſoules, but to emptie purſes; not to bridle the pride of his Subiects, but to looſe the raines to his owne vnbridled appetites, and of a priuate Romane Biſhop, to make himſelfe the abſolute ſpirituall Head, and high Prieſt of the whole world: thus like another <hi>Lucifer,</hi> he erecting and raiſing vp himſelfe aboue all that which is called God. Neither doeth he prohibite the Bible, the precious pearle of Gods word, becauſe it ought not to be giuen to ſwine, but in that himſelfe is one, and would haue others to be ſo too: not becauſe the ſame is darke and obſcure, but in that he, like a cloſe and ſlie theefe, loues darkeneſſe better then light, for the attaining to his proper ends and deſſeignes, and the more eaſily to tyrannize ouer the world.</p>
               <p>But they that are deſirous and zealous of their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought with a gratefull and cheerefull heart, to receiue ſo high and inexplicable a benefite, out of Gods diuine bounty conferred on vs, in declaring vnto vs by the ſacred word, his heauenly will and pleaſure, (which is pleaſing and acceptable to him, and the ſame odious and offenſiue to the other,) that ſo following the one, and flying the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we may both li<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and die in his loue and fauour, and by this meanes attaine to be partakers of his glory; the greatneſſe of which benefit, and ſupereminencie of which honour, <hi>Moſes</hi> declared vnto the people in theſe expreſſe words, <hi>What Nation is there ſo noble and happy, that enioyes the ſame Ceremonies, Iudgements, and Lawes of God, which I will this day ſet before your eyes?</hi> And in the Pſalme 148. the royall Prophet yeeldeth praiſe vnto God, ſaying, that <hi>hee had denounced his word to Iacob, and his Iudgements to Iſrael:</hi> which grace and fauour he had not ſhewed to any other nation of the world. So as this high and ſpeciall fauour ſhewed vs by God, in communicating himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6367:37"/>vs by his holy word, ought to bind vs to be the more carefull in ſeeking him out, euen as he commandeth vs; and that we might the better doe it, hee gaue order, they ſhould be diuulged in our vulgar tongues, and the holy Doctors exhorts to the ſame; moouing vs thereunto by the example of thoſe in the Primitiue Church, and others that liued many ages after, and alſo we are hereunto inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the rare and innumerable benefits which doe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceed therefrom, deriued from the true knowledge we haue therein of God, and of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, if we deſire to be knowen of him with approbation, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, and that note vs to be his elect, through the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation wherein wee all ſtand bound, to obſerue his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſeruice and worſhip, ſubmitting all thoſe temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ordinarily aſſaile vs, to his holy will and moſt ſacred Law, if we meane to obtaine victory ouer our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, groſſe ignorance and blindneſſe, and without which this light, muſt needs haue a great power and domination ouer vs. Finally it binds vs, neuer to let this ſacred booke of the holy Scriptures to be out of our hands; the reading and meditation therein, being our moſt important felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and happineſſe, as may plainely appeare by all that which hath beene ſaid, and <hi>Fonſeca</hi> teacheth no leſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fonſeca</hi> ſegun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da parte trata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do del amor de Dios, fol. <hi>57.</hi>
                  </note> who is yet liuing in the Spaniſh Court, and eſteemed for one of the greateſt Diuines, and rareſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of our time.</p>
               <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6367:38"/>
            <head>Los Libros de que he ſacado lo que en eſte tratado ſe contiene ſon los que ſe ſiguen.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Bookes out of which this Treatiſe is <hi>gathered, are theſe following.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HIstoria Pontifical y catclica compuesta por el Doctor <hi>Ylleſcas</hi> en Madrid. <hi>An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Teſoro de ignorantes compueſto por el P. Fr. <hi>Chryſtoual Marquez,</hi> impreſſo en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1614.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bienes del honeſto traba<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, y dan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os de la ocioſidad por el P. <hi>Pedro Guzman</hi> en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1614.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Guia eſpiritual del P. <hi>Puente</hi> en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1614.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obras del Maeſtro <hi>Gracian,</hi> en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1616.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tomo primero de la historia general de <hi>Eſpan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a</hi> por el P. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi> en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1623.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſideraciones ſobre los myſterios de la miſſa por el P. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Antonio</hi> en <hi>Madrid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1598.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tomoprimero del Arte de bien viuir por el P. Maeſtro <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uardo</hi> en <hi>Valladolid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>El Maeſtro Christiano del Maestro <hi>Reynoſa</hi> en <hi>Vallado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1618.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obras morales del Maeſtro Fr. <hi>Manuel Rodriguez</hi> en <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladolid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1621.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luz de las marauillas que Dios obra en el alma por el P. Maestro Fr. <hi>Leandro de Granada</hi> en <hi>Valladolid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6367:38"/>
            <p> Segundo Tomo de la perfecion por el P. <hi>Puente</hi> en <hi>Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Los Nombres de Christo por el P. Maeſtro Fr. <hi>Luys de Leon</hi> en <hi>Salamanca. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1603.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suma del P. Maeſtro Fr. <hi>Pedro de Ledeſma</hi> en <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1589.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Catorce diſcurſos ſobre el <hi>Pater noſter</hi> por el P. Fr. <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar Pacheco</hi> en <hi>Salamanca, An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1594.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vigilia magna del P. Fr. <hi>Nicolas Brauo</hi> en <hi>Salamanca. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1605.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Libro del Roſario de nueſtra ſen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ora por el P. <hi>Arinzano</hi> en <hi>Salamanca. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1903.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tratado del officio Eccleſiaſtico Canonico por el Doctor Don <hi>Bernardino de Sandoual</hi> en <hi>Toledo, An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1568.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Primeraparte de las excelencias de la caſtidad, por el P. Fr. <hi>Ioſeph de Ieſus Maria,</hi> en <hi>Alcala de Henares. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1601.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Primera parte del Libro de la vanidad del mundo, por el P. <hi>Eſtella</hi> en <hi>Alcala de Henares. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1597.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſinuacion y demonſtracion de la Diuina piedad por el P. Maeſtro Fr. <hi>Leandro de Granada</hi> en <hi>Seuilla. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1616.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Philoſophia moral de Principes por el P. <hi>Torres</hi> en <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1596.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>La introduccion del Symbolo de la Fe por el P. Maeſtro Fr. <hi>Luys de Granada,</hi> en <hi>Lerma. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1619.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tratado del Purgatorio contra <hi>Luthero,</hi> por Fr. <hi>Dimas Serpi</hi> en <hi>Barcelona. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1611.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Historia de la adoracion y vſo de las Imagines por el Maeſtro <hi>Prades</hi> en <hi>Valencia. 1597.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Segunda parte del tratado del Amor de Dios, por el P. Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro <hi>Fonſeca</hi> en <hi>Valencia. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1608.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tomo tercero y quarto de la perfecion Chriſtiana, por el P. <hi>Puente</hi> en <hi>Pamplona. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1616.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:6367:39"/>
            <p> Segunda parte del Monte Caluario, por Don <hi>Antonio de Gueuara,</hi> en <hi>Anueres. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1559.</hi> Con Preuilegio.</p>
            <p>Iſagoge in totam ſacram Scripturam, Autore <hi>Ludouico de Tena</hi> Epiſcopo <hi>Dertuſenſi,</hi> en <hi>Hueſca. An<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o 1622.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, Printed by THOMAS HARPER. M. DC. XXIV.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
